<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Wisdome's judgment of folly. Delivered in a sermon at the spital, in the solemn assembly of the city, on Munday in Easter-week, April XI. A.D. MDCLIII. By Thomas Horton D.D.</title>
            <author>Horton, Thomas, d. 1673.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1653</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 140 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 34 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A86580</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2884</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E691_4</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206965</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866043</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866043</idno>
            <idno type="VID">166481</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A86580)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 166481)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 107:E691[4])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Wisdome's judgment of folly. Delivered in a sermon at the spital, in the solemn assembly of the city, on Munday in Easter-week, April XI. A.D. MDCLIII. By Thomas Horton D.D.</title>
                  <author>Horton, Thomas, d. 1673.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 31, 40-71, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T. Maxey for Samuel Gellibrand, at the Ball in S. Pauls Church-yard.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1653.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Text continuous despite pagination.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A sermon preached at the spital.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Corinthians, 1st III, 18-19 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:166481:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>WISDOME'S <hi>JVDGMENT</hi> OF FOLLY. DELIVERED In a SERMON at the SPITAL, In the Solemn ASSEMBLY of the CITY, on <hi>Munday</hi> in <hi>Eaſter-Week, April</hi> XI. <hi>A.D.</hi> MDCLIII.</p>
            <p>By <hi>THOMAS HORTON,</hi> D.D.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PROV. 1 20, 21. and 8.2, 3.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>WISDOM cryeth <hi>without,</hi> ſhe uttereth her voyce in the <hi>Streets,</hi> ſhe cryeth in the <hi>chief place of concourſe,</hi> in the <hi>opening of the Gates;</hi> in the <hi>City</hi> ſhe uttereth her words. She ſtandeth in the top of <hi>high places,</hi> by the <hi>wayes,</hi> in the places of the <hi>paths.</hi> She cryeth at the <hi>Gates,</hi> at the <hi>entering in</hi> of the <hi>City,</hi> at the coming in of the doors: O ye <hi>ſimple, underſtand Wiſdom, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. 9.23.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Thus ſaith the LORD, Let not the wiſe man glorie in his wiſdom.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 COR. 1.27.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>God hath choſen the fooliſh things of the world to confound the Wiſe.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. Maxey</hi> for SAMUEL GELLIBRAND, at the BALL in S. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1653.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:166481:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:166481:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honorable JOHN FOWKES LORD MAYOR, Together with the Court of ALDERMEN of the famous City of LONDON.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>RIGHT HONORABLE,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
               </hi> Here preſent you with a Sermon, which is many ways <hi>Yours,</hi> but two eſpecially: The one, as it was firſt <hi>preached</hi> upon your <hi>Invitation;</hi> and the other, as it is now <hi>Printed</hi> upon your <hi>Importunity.</hi> The <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject</hi> it treats of is <hi>WISDOME,</hi> which (if it may prove ſo in the <hi>Event,</hi> and a <hi>wiſe man</hi> may be Judg in his <hi>own Cauſe,</hi> and magnifying of his owne Perfections) <hi>is much better then</hi> either<note n="a" place="margin">Eccleſ. 9.15, 16, 18.</note> 
               <hi>STRENGTH</hi> or <hi>WEAPONS OF WAR;</hi> and <hi>whereby</hi> (for the greater Incouragement of thoſe which are <hi>Rich</hi>) even the <hi>Poor</hi> have ſometimes been able <hi>to deliver the City.</hi> All the matter is <hi>this, What</hi> this Wiſdom <hi>is,</hi> and wherein it conſiſts. The <hi>World</hi> commonly <hi>miſtakes</hi> it, and layes it in that <hi>moſt,</hi> which hath leaſt title to it of any thing elſe; from
<pb facs="tcp:166481:3"/>whence it juſtly incurres the cenſure of the <hi>contrary Denomination,</hi> and that in the ſenſe of <hi>Him who is beſt able to judg of both.</hi> In this ſhort and ſlender <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> (which ye have here before you) you may perhaps finde ſomething, which may in ſome meaſure tend to the unfolding of this difficulty to you, and a right De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination of the Cauſe: which if it ſhall pleaſe God by his <hi>Spirit</hi> to ſet on effectually upon any of your <hi>hearts,</hi> (as you have cheerfully entertain'd it with your <hi>Ears</hi>) or upon the Hearts of any <hi>others,</hi> whoſe <hi>eys</hi> together with yours may be made partakers of it, I ſhall not then altogether <hi>repent</hi> me of expoſing my ſelf in this manner to <hi>publick view;</hi> which yet otherwiſe, in an <hi>Age</hi> which abounds ſo much with <hi>Sermons</hi> and <hi>Cenſori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe</hi> both at once, I very wel might. The Lord who is the <hi>God of wiſdom,</hi> give us all the <hi>Spirit of wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> anſwerable to the ſeveral Services whereunto he deſignes us: And powr forth a large Meaſure of <hi>this Spirit</hi> more abundantly, &amp; eſpecially upon <hi>Your ſelvs,</hi> for the menaging of thoſe great Affairs which theſe <hi>Times</hi> put you upon in the Government of this populous City; The welfare and happineſſe whereof, with your Own (as a part of it) ſhall be alwayes moſt unfainedly deſired by</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Servant in and for Chriſt, THO. HORTON.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:166481:3"/>
            <head>A SERMON Preached at the <hi>SPITAL,</hi> on the XI. of <hi>April,</hi> being Munday in EASTER-WEEK, <hi>A. D.</hi> MDCLIII.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 COR. 3. ver. 18, 19.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>Let no man deceive himſelf; if any man among you ſeemeth to be wiſe in this world, let him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a fool, that he may be wiſe;</p>
                  <p>For the wiſedome of this world is fooliſhneſs with God.—</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is the part and manner of all <hi>Wiſe and skilful Workmen,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction.</note> that they may carry their work on with ſo much happier ſucceſs, and may the better go through with it, to have ſpecial heed and regard to it in the <hi>Grounds and Principles</hi> of it. That Houſe will be beſt ſettled, which is ſtrengthned and made good in the <hi>Foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:</hi> That Diſeaſe will be beſt cured which is removed
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:166481:4"/>and taken away in the <hi>Root and Cauſes</hi> of the Diſtemper: That Wound or Sore wil be moſt readily and happily healed, which is firſt ſearched and examined at the <hi>core and bottom</hi> of it. And as it is thus in <hi>Corporals and Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porals,</hi> and the things of this Life; ſo alſo in <hi>Spirituals,</hi> and the things of a Better; as in the diſtempers of <hi>Body,</hi> ſo in the diſtempers either of <hi>Church</hi> or <hi>State.</hi> This the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> who was a <hi>Wiſe Maſter-Builder</hi> in the houſe of God (as he ſtiles himſelfe in the tenth verſe of this Chapter) who was an able and skilful <hi>Chirurgian and Phyſician</hi> about the Body of Chriſt, as appears by his daily exerciſe in it, was very ſenſible and apprehenſive of,<note place="margin">The Cohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence.</note> for his own behalf. Therefore being now deſirous to correct ſome groſſer Abuſes and corruptions, which were at this time crept into the Church of <hi>Corinth</hi> in point both of <hi>Doctrine and Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners,</hi> he does very carefully apply himſelf to the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of this Obſervation; where he does not immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately fall upon the conſideration of the <hi>Evils them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,</hi> which were prevailing amongſt them, but firſt of all very ſeaſonably ſtrikes at the <hi>General riſe</hi> and Original of them and the Spring and Fountain whence thoſe evils did proceed in them. Now becauſe this indeed was a grand miſtake of themſelves, and an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verweening conceit and opinion of their own worldly <hi>wiſdome,</hi> to the ſlighting of <hi>Gods wiſdome in Chriſt,</hi> and the diſpenſation of the Goſpel, he does therefore in this Text, which I have now read unto you, begin with them, and deal with them moſt effectually in this particular. <hi>Hic ulcus ipſum digito attingit,</hi> as <hi>Calvin</hi> well upon the place. Here he layes his finger upon the ſore, ſtrikes the nail on the head, and comes home to the very root, and bottom, and foundation
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:166481:4"/>of the buſineſs it ſelf, <hi>Let no man deceive himſelf, if any man, &amp;c.</hi> This is the proper Coherence and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendence of theſe words in this Scripture.</p>
            <p>Now in the Text it ſelf we have three General Parts conſiderable of us.<note place="margin">The Diviſion</note>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, A word of <hi>Caution</hi> or Admonition.<note place="margin">Three Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Parts.</note> Secondly, A word of <hi>Counſel</hi> or Exhortation. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, A word of <hi>Inforcement.</hi> The <hi>Caution,</hi> that we have in thoſe words, <hi>Let no man deceive himſelf.</hi> The <hi>Counſel,</hi> that we have in theſe, <hi>If any man among you ſeemeth to be wiſe in this world, let him become a fool, &amp;c.</hi> The <hi>Inforcement</hi> or Argument to perſwade, in theſe, <hi>For the wiſdome of this world is fooliſhneſs with God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>WE begin in order with the firſt,<note place="margin">The firſt Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Part.</note> 
               <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> or <hi>Admonition</hi> which is here exhibited, <hi>Let no man deceive himſelf.</hi>] This ſpeech, it is not <hi>ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute</hi> but <hi>reſpective;</hi> It has a double aſpect with it, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">The Refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence double. Backward. Forward,</note> and it caſts either backward or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. If you take it as looking <hi>backward</hi> upon that which went before, ſo it has in it the force of a cloſe &amp; ſerous concluſion, as leaving a very good tang and relliſh behind it. If you take it as looking forward upon that which immediately follows, ſo it has in it the force of a <hi>Preface,</hi> and preparatory introduction, as making a very good entrance and paſſage for that which comes after. Take it which way you will, as either way you may take it (though I incline rather to the latter, which is by way of Introduction and Pream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the ſucceeding Exhortation) the Caution is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good and ſeaſonable, and ſuch as may be very well adminiſtred to any perſons whoſoever they be.
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:166481:5"/>Indeed, at the firſt hearing it may ſeem to be a little <hi>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous,</hi> and ſuch as might well have been ſpared: Let no man deceive <hi>himſelf:</hi> Why; is there any great fear of <hi>that?</hi> Can we think that any one ſhould be ſo mad or fooliſh, as ever to do <hi>ſo?</hi> If Saint <hi>Paul</hi> had ſaid, Let no man deceive his <hi>Neighbour, then</hi> perhaps he had ſaid <hi>ſomewhat:</hi> if he had ſaid <hi>here,</hi> as we find him to have ſaid <hi>elſewhere;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Theſ. 4.6.</note> 
               <hi>Let no man go beyond or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraud his BROTHER in any matter,</hi> we might <hi>then</hi> have thought he had ſpoken <hi>to purpoſe.</hi> But to give ſo ſtrict a charge and caution againſt <hi>ſelf-deceiving,</hi> what need was there of <hi>that?</hi> Beloved, the Apoſtle knew very well <hi>what</hi> he ſaid, and he knew alſo <hi>to whom</hi> he ſaid it; and this is that which he ſayes, Let no man deceive <hi>himſelf;</hi> which he ſpeaks not only to the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians</hi> (that we may not by the way <hi>deceive our ſelves</hi> in regard of the <hi>Perſons ſpoken to</hi>) but he ſpeaks it to every one of <hi>Us. Mutate nomine de TE.</hi> It is a Caution of a <hi>General Latitude</hi> and Extent, which it carries with it to all Ages and Times whatſoever, even to <hi>theſe</hi> more particularly and eſpecially wherein we live; then in which, as there was never more defrau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and deceiving of <hi>others,</hi> ſo neither more decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of <hi>mens ſelves.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Self-deceit a general Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe.</note> This <hi>Self-deceit</hi> it is the <hi>common</hi> and <hi>general</hi> Diſeaſe that reigns amongſt us: yea, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, upon proof we ſhall find it to be the <hi>ground</hi> and foundation of all <hi>other</hi> deceit in the world. What ever deceit is <hi>abroad,</hi> it begins at <hi>home,</hi> and takes its riſe and original from <hi>thence.</hi> If men were true to their <hi>own intereſts,</hi> they would never be falſe to <hi>others:</hi> If they were faithful in what belongs to <hi>themſelves,</hi> they might be truſted with their <hi>neighbours;</hi> but now whilſt they firſt try concluſions upon their <hi>own hearts</hi> for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:166481:5"/>of <hi>them,</hi> they do more readily practiſe it up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their <hi>brethren</hi> for the deceiving of <hi>them,</hi> with them.</p>
            <p>Therefore it is that the Scripture does ſo often lay ſuch a Caution and proviſo as this is, <hi>Do not erre; Be not deceived; Let no man beguile you;</hi> and here, <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive not your ſelves.</hi> All ſtill for this reaſon, to ſignifie the general <hi>proneneſs</hi> and diſpoſition which is in our Nature hereunto; as oftentimes to be cozened and deceived, and beguiled by <hi>others;</hi> ſo as often a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the reſt by our ſelves, to be the <hi>Deceived</hi> and the <hi>Deceivers</hi> both at once.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> himſelf gives us a very good account of it from whence it proceeds;<note place="margin">The ground of ſelf-deceit.</note> namely, from the nature and quality of the <hi>heart</hi> it ſelf, which is <hi>fraudu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and deceitful above all things.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. 17.9.</note> A <hi>deceitful heart</hi> will not ſpare ſo much as <hi>it ſelf,</hi> but will be ready to deceive <hi>that:</hi> And this is that which <hi>all</hi> (more or leſs) have remaining in them. Thoſe which are in a ſtate of <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Unregeneracy,</hi> they are <hi>nothing elſe</hi> but deceit; their hearts do continually <hi>frame</hi> and <hi>faſhion</hi> deceit in them, as the <hi>Scripture</hi> ſpeaks. Thoſe whoſe natures are <hi>changed by Grace,</hi> yet they have ſome <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks</hi> and remainders of the <hi>Old man</hi> abiding in them, which is corrupt, according to the <hi>deceitful luſts.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 4.22.</note> Ever ſince the <hi>Serpent</hi> deceived us, we have ſtill been rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, more or leſs, to deceive our ſelves.</p>
            <p>Would you know by what <hi>Means</hi> and in what <hi>wayes</hi> this is done?<note place="margin">The wayes of ſelf-deceit.</note> Take it briefly thus:</p>
            <p>Firſt, By <hi>falſe conceits and apprehenſions</hi> which men have of themſelves.<note place="margin">1. By falſe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions.</note> 
               <hi>Self-flattery</hi> hath a great ſtroke and influence upon <hi>ſelf-deceit. He that thinks himſelf to be ſomething when he is nothing,</hi> he <hi>deceives himſelf,</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:166481:6"/>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, It is the Apoſtles own judgement and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion which he give of it in another place, and it is that which he hath a ſpecial reſpect to here in this, as we may ſee by that which followes, and ſhall ſee more by and by. <hi>If any man among you ſeemeth to be wiſe,</hi> &amp;c. ſo then, <hi>Let no man deceive himſelf;</hi> that is, by too high a conceit and apprehenſion of his owne wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, thinking himſelfe wiſer then he is, or hath cauſe to think himſelfe. This is that which many perſons oftentimes are ſubject unto, and thereby to <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive themſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">2 By falſe hopes.</note> By <hi>falſe hopes and promiſes</hi> which men make to themſelves. It is a great deceiving of any, when they ſhall expect and look for more then they are I kely to enjoy; it was that wherein the Divel did at firſt deceive our firſt Parents <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> in <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe,</hi> by raiſing their hopes and expectations beyond that which it was probable they ſhould partake of: And thus in like manner do men alſo deceive them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,<note place="margin">See <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.26, appliable to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriage.</note> by vain and groundleſs perſwaſions of their owne happineſs and the welfare of the condition in which they are, eſpecially in reference to <hi>Spirituals</hi> and a better life. There are divers which are ready to think the caſe is here very well with them, with whom in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed it is far otherwiſe; take it for granted that their ſtate is good in order to ſalvation, who yet never were careful in all their lives to work out their ſalvation, or to walk in ſuch wayes as might tend to ſuch an end as that is, but rather quite oppoſite to it. There is many a one who makes as full an account to <hi>go to Heaven</hi> when he goes out of the world, as he does to <hi>go out of the world</hi> (nay it may be a great deal more) who yet if God be not more merciful unto him, muſt go to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:166481:6"/>
               <hi>another place.</hi> It is a Point which were worth the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing (if we had nothing elſe to ſpeak of) eſpecially in this <hi>confident age</hi> which is fallen upon us, wherein ſo many both <hi>opinions</hi> and <hi>practices</hi> are ſwallowed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any <hi>ſcruple,</hi> even to rowſe and awaken men in this particular, and to cure them (if it were poſſible) of this <hi>ſelf-deceit.</hi> But we have not leiſure for it, and muſt leave it to a <hi>better hand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, By <hi>falſe performances</hi> and duties, men de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive themſelves alſo here.<note place="margin">3 By falſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formances.</note> He that does not any thing as he <hi>ſhould,</hi> he does thereby <hi>deceive himſelf</hi> in the doing of it. <hi>Slothfulneſs</hi> and <hi>deceitfulneſs</hi> they come both of them to one effect; and ſo the ſame word in the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Language ſignifies both,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and is taken promiſcuouſly; as <hi>Jer.</hi> 48.10. where ſome read it <hi>thus,</hi> Curſed is he that doth the work of the Lord <hi>negligently:</hi> there are others that read it <hi>thus,</hi> Curſed is he that doth the work of the Lord <hi>deceitfully;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe to do it <hi>negligently</hi> is indeed to do it <hi>deceitfully.</hi> And ſo the Prophet <hi>Malachi</hi> implies likewiſe, <hi>Mal.</hi> 1.14 <hi>Curſed be the deceiver, which hath in his flock a Male, and voweth and ſacrificeth unto the Lord a corrupt thing.</hi> The <hi>Deceiver,</hi> that is, the <hi>formall Worſhipper,</hi> which is careleſs and negligent and cuſtomary in the Service of God; ſuch an one as this is, he is the <hi>deceiver,</hi> and ſo accounted. And as a deceiver of <hi>others,</hi> ſo eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and particularly of <hi>himſelf:</hi> Ye have an expreſs place to this purpoſe, as to <hi>one part</hi> of Religion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the reſt, and that is, as to the <hi>hearing of the word,</hi> Jam. 1.22. <hi>Be ye doers of the word, and not hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers only, deceiving your own ſelves.</hi> Whoever is a <hi>careleſſe hearer,</hi> he is upon this account a <hi>ſelf-deceiver,</hi> and ſo is every one elſe that does allow and content
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:166481:7"/>himſelf in any perfunctory and ſuperficial performance of any part of Gods worſhip beſides. He deceives him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf both of the <hi>comfort</hi> and ſweetneſs which is contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the duty it ſelf, and of the <hi>reward</hi> alſo which is annexed unto it. Thus have we briefly ſeen by what means, and in what wayes eſpecially, men may be ſaid to <hi>deceive themſelves;</hi> although, as I conceive, the firſt of them is that which is chiefly aimed at, and more principally intended in this place.</p>
            <p>Now that which lies upon us in reference hereunto,<note place="margin">The Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence.</note> is in ſpecial manner to obſerve and take notice of the Apoſtles Caveat, and to ſuffer it to prevail with us, that we avoid this rock our ſelves which we have heard how prone we are to ſplit upon; eſpecially con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering the grievous aggravations which are atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant upon it;<note place="margin">Aggravation of ſelf deceit.</note> for as all Deceit is very odious, ſo <hi>ſelf-deceit</hi> more then any other. And that in theſe follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing reſpects</p>
            <p>Firſt,<note place="margin">1. Unnatural.</note> It is moſt <hi>unnaturall:</hi> It carryes a kind of Monſtrouſneſs, and Barbarouſneſs with it. Every evil is ſtill ſo much the worſe as there is the greater en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement againſt it, and hath ſomewhat within a mans own breſt to take him off from it. The leſs tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion there is <hi>unto</hi> ſin, the greater provocation there is in it: and the more <hi>cauſe</hi> there is to <hi>forbear</hi> it, the more <hi>iniquity</hi> it is to <hi>commit</hi> it. Now ſuch are thoſe ſins which men are guilty of in regard of themſelves; they are in this reſpect ſins of an higher rank. How does the Apoſtle aggravate the ſin of <hi>fornication?</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 6.18.</note> From hence, that it is a ſin againſt <hi>ones ſelf</hi> in a pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar manner. The like may be alſo ſaid of ſelf-decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, which therefore makes it ſo much the more hai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous. The neerer at any time the relation is, the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:166481:7"/>worſe alwais is the deceit; as moſt contrary to the Principles of Nature, and thoſe diſpoſitions which God hath placed in the heart: which is one thing in this ſelf-deceit.</p>
            <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">2 Leaſt ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected.</note> It is the leaſt <hi>diſcerned or expected.</hi> Thoſe evils are moſt to be avoyded, which are worſt to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected, which a man can hardlieſt find out the root and bottom of them.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Socr. in Plato.</note> Why ſuch now is this <hi>ſelf-de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit,</hi> it is a cloſe and ſecret evil, which no body almoſt is aware of, or does think will come upon him, and therefore not ſo eaſily prevented without a great deal of heed and care. Beſides that (as he ſaid) <hi>The Chea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is alwaies at hand,</hi> and ſticks faſt and cloſe by ones<note n="a" place="margin">Quomodo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertam me ab inimico meo, cum inimicus meus ſit inter la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tera mea? <hi>Arab. Poet. Ano<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ym.</hi>
               </note> ſides, without ſeparation.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, It is moſt pernicious, becauſe it is in <hi>regra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vi,</hi>
               <note place="margin">3. Moſt perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious.</note> it is alwaies in a matter of <hi>conſequence</hi> and ſpecial importance; for a man to be deceiv'd but in <hi>a trifle,</hi> though he would not <hi>like</hi> it, yet he might be able to <hi>bear</hi> it: But to be deceived in matter <hi>of life and death,</hi> this is intolerable. Yet this now is that which is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable in this ſelf-deceit, He that deceives <hi>himſelf,</hi> deceives his <hi>ſoul,</hi> which is the <hi>better part</hi> of himſelf, and wherein deceit of all other elſe is leaſt diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſable<note n="b" place="margin">Curritis pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pter <hi>Animam;</hi> Tota exaggera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio haec eſt quòd dicitur <hi>propter Animam.</hi> Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtin.</note>.</p>
            <p>I ſhall not need to ſay much more for the preſſing of this point upon you,<note place="margin">Means of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voyding it.</note> except it be onely by ſhewing you how to ſhun ſuch a miſchievous evil as this is, and to prevent it in your ſelves;<note place="margin">1. Spirituall Watchfulneſs.</note> which is done no better way, than by carrying a <hi>narrow watch</hi> over your own hearts. He that would not <hi>deceive</hi> himſelf, he muſt take heed of <hi>truſting</hi> himſelf; if he does, he will be ſoon overtaken and inſnar'd before he is aware. He that truſts in his own heart, is a Fool, ſayes <hi>Salomon,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:166481:8"/>Prov.</hi> 28.26. And ſo indeed he is, and at laſt will prove to be ſo. Look then, as you would do with one who is a known and profeſt Jugler, or Cheater; you will truſt him no further than you ſee him, never have your eye off on him, as long as you have any thing to do with him; In like manner muſt ye alſo deal with your own falſe and deceitful hearts. It is a good rule here, which is given and obſerv'd <hi>by Politicians,</hi> as concerns their converſe in the world,<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Epicha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m.</note> 
               <hi>Be watchful, and remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber to miſtruſt.</hi> Becauſe there's a great deal of Treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and falſe dealing which ye are likely to meet with, if ye look not better to it, therefore our beſt defence will here be our own jealouſie and ſelf-ſuſpicion. <hi>Sola iſtîc ſecuritas eſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Groſted. Epiſc. Linc.</note> 
               <hi>nunquam eſſe ſecurum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And eſpecially deſire of <hi>God himſelf</hi> to watch over us,<note place="margin">2. Recourſe to God.</note> and by the ſweet and gracious guidance of his holy Spirit, to inſtruct and direct us, to ſhew us our own hearts, with all the windings and turnings of them; who alone <hi>ſearches and knows</hi> them: To ſhew us them, not in the <hi>event,</hi> (which is very ſad and grievous) but <hi>afore-hand</hi> in the pre-diſcoveries and apprehenſions of it:<note place="margin">Pſal. 1 39.23, 24.</note> Say here with the holy man <hi>David, Search me O God, and know my heart, try me, and know my thoughts: See if there be any wicked way in me, and lead me in the way everlaſting.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I forget my ſelf, conſidering, that as yet I am but onely in the <hi>Threſhold</hi> of the Text, and the open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the door unto it. So much for the <hi>Firſt General</hi> propounded, <hi>viz.</hi> The word of <hi>Caution</hi> or Admoniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Let no man deceive himſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>WE come now to the <hi>ſecond,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The <hi>2<hi rend="sup">d</hi>
                  </hi> Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Part.</note> which gives us fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Entrance and Admiſſion into it, and that's
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:166481:8"/>the word <hi>of Councel or Exhortation,</hi> in theſe words, <hi>If any man among you ſeemeth to be wiſe in this world, let him become a fool that he may be wiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein again we have three Branches more: Firſt,<note place="margin">Three Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of this. <hi>1.</hi> Branch</note> The Perſon ſpoken to, <hi>If any man.</hi> Secondly, The Advice which is given him, <hi>Let him become a fool.</hi> Thirdly, The End or Motive, <hi>That he may be wiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the firſt,<note place="margin">1 The Perſon ſpoken to.</note> The <hi>Perſon ſpoken</hi> to, <hi>If any man among you ſeem to be wiſe in this world.</hi> Here's an implicite <hi>Cenſure</hi> of three things in this expreſſion.<note place="margin">Three things more here cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured.</note> Firſt, of the <hi>Miſtake</hi> of falſe wiſdom for true, or of that which is leſs weighty and conſiderable, for that which is more. Secondly, of <hi>the pretence</hi> to true wiſdom in the want of it, <hi>Seeming</hi> to be wiſe, whenas indeed there is no <hi>ſuch matter.</hi> Thirdly, of <hi>Conceitedneſs and ſelf-applauſe</hi> in that wiſdom which is injoy'd and partaken-of, whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it be. Each of theſe are in this ſuppoſition.</p>
            <p>Firſt of all,<note place="margin">I. The miſtake of Wiſdom.</note> I ſay, here's a <hi>cenſure</hi> of the miſtake of wiſdom it ſelf, <hi>Wiſe in this world.</hi> [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] It is <hi>terminus Diminutivus,</hi> an expreſſion of ſome Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minution and Diſparagement which it carryes along with it; which therefore would be a little opened and explained by us what it is.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To be wiſe in this world,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Wiſdom in this world double: as to the <hi>Time</hi> and <hi>place, Nature</hi> and <hi>kinde of</hi> Wiſdom.</note> according to the ſound of the words, has a double reſpect in it: Either firſt to the <hi>Time and Place</hi> of wiſdom: or Secondly, to the <hi>Nature and Kinds</hi> of wiſdom. If we take it according to the firſt ſenſe, onely for the <hi>time and place,</hi> To be wiſe in the world, that is, to be wiſe whilſt <hi>we live</hi> in the world; ſo there is nothing that is juſtly taxable or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provable in it, but rather the contrary; for it is that which we <hi>muſt</hi> be, if ever we be that which we <hi>ſhould</hi> be; and it will be the worſe for us, we be not: Take
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:166481:9"/>it for <hi>the trueſt and beſt</hi> wiſdom of all, (which we ſhall ſpeak to more anon) wiſdom towards <hi>God and ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi> it is that which muſt be firſt <hi>in this world,</hi> if it be ever at all: He thats not <hi>thus</hi> wiſe in <hi>this world,</hi> he will be but a fool in <hi>the next,</hi> who ever he be. The ſpace and ſeaſon of our <hi>abode here below,</hi> is that which God hath appointed for our improvement in <hi>Spiritual wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> and which accordingly we are to make uſe of for ſuch a purpoſe. <hi>Be wiſe now,</hi> O ye Judges, &amp;c. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.10. Therefore it is not to be taken in this ſenſe, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to <hi>the Time of Wiſdom</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond is as to <hi>the nature and kind</hi> of wiſdom, wiſe in this world,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> i.e. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> that is, <hi>wiſe with worldly wiſdom.</hi> This is that which the Apoſtle ſeems to diſparage, and to take off the <hi>Corinthians</hi> from, with all other Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians beſides, in the Extravagancies, and Inordinacies of it; ſuch a wiſdom namely, as does take its riſe, and ground, and progreſs from this preſent world. All the Queſtion here,<note place="margin">The nature &amp; kinde reduced to three Heads ſpecially.</note> will be, What it is? Now for this, if we take it in its latitude, it may be <hi>reduced to three heads</hi> eſpecially.</p>
            <p>The firſt is the <hi>wiſdom of the mind,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. The wiſdom of the Mind.</note> 
               <hi>Natural</hi> wiſdom, which lies in Parts, and Learning, and humane Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and ſuch accompliſhments as thoſe, the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>Man, Sapientia hominis</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Twofold:
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Of</hi> Words,</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Of</hi> Notions.</item>
                  </list>
               </note>, as it is call'd 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.4, 5. And this again of two ſorts. Firſt, The wiſdom of <hi>words, Sapientia verborum,</hi> as it is called 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.17. Secondly, The wiſdom of <hi>Notions, Sapientia conceptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um,</hi> which carryes the ſtrength of ſome <hi>Reaſon and demonſtration</hi> with it; there's <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Now either, or both of theſe taken together, make up to us this <hi>Natural wiſdom,</hi> which is in a ſenſe alſo <hi>the wiſdom of the world,</hi> for as much as it is ſuch, as
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:166481:9"/>is <hi>only exerciſed here in this world,</hi> [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] according to the Elements and Rudiments of the world, as it is there expreſt in <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 2.8. being that whereby the world does in a Spiritual manner ſubſiſt, whereas in the world to come there will be no need at all of it: <hi>VVhether there be Prophecies, they ſhal fail; whether there be tongues, they ſhal ceaſe; whether there be knowledg, it ſhal vaniſh away,</hi> 1 Cor. 13.8. That is one branch of this wiſdom.</p>
            <p>The ſecond is, the <hi>Wiſdome of the fleſh, carnal</hi> wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome;<note place="margin">2. The wiſdom of the Fleſh,</note> this is another ſort of this wiſdom of the world <hi>Sapientia carnis;</hi> and we find it named ſo in Scripture [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,] the <hi>minding</hi> of the fleſh, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.7 And [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] <hi>Fleſhly wiſdome,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.12. And [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] <hi>Making proviſion for the Fleſh,</hi> Rom 13.14. That wiſdome which does conſiſt in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivances and proſecutions of <hi>Luſt,</hi> which if it be <hi>Bodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> or ſuch as is feated in the <hi>inferior faculties</hi> of the ſoul, then it is called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Senſual wiſdome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>twofold:</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>Senſuall.</item>
                     <item>Diveliiſh.</item>
                  </list>
               </note> 
               <hi>Jam.</hi> 3.15. If it be <hi>Spiritual,</hi> and ſuch as lyes rather in the <hi>Superiour</hi> faculties, of <hi>Will and underſtanding;</hi> then it is called (in the ſame place of Scripture) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Divelliſh wiſdom,</hi> the wiſdome of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel, as that before,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Epheſ. 2 3.</note> the wiſdome of <hi>Man;</hi> the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle <hi>Paul</hi> joines them both together in one place, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.3. The luſts or deſires of the <hi>fleſh, and of the mind.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third and laſt kind of Wiſdome which is here ſtruck at by the Apoſtle,<note place="margin">3 The wiſdom of the World, <hi>in terminis.</hi>
               </note> is that which is ſo properly, and <hi>in terminis,</hi> and in the firſt acception of it, <hi>world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wiſdome,</hi> which does conſiſt in the inordinate pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit and proſecution of worldly contentments, and theſe accommodations here below, whether of Riches, or
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:166481:10"/>Honors, or Pleaſures, or any ſuch things; this is called in the place before cited) <hi>Earthly wiſdom,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Jam.</hi> 3.15. and the Profeſſors of it, ſuch as <hi>mind</hi> earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly things, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.19. This again is of two ſorts,<note place="margin">Twofold: <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Of the</hi> World,</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Of the</hi> Age,</item>
                  </list>
               </note> as conſiderable under a double notion, each of them expreſt in the Text; the one is <hi>Sapientia Mundi,</hi> The wiſdome of the <hi>world,</hi> in <hi>ver.</hi> 19. and the other is, <hi>Sapientia Seculi,</hi> the wiſdome of the <hi>Age</hi> or <hi>Time,</hi> expreſt in <hi>ver.</hi> 18.</p>
            <p>Firſt,<note place="margin">1. The Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of the World.</note> The wiſdom of the <hi>world</hi> conſidered at large. The Apoſtle ſtrikes at ſuch who are ſo addicted and wedded to <hi>this:</hi> If any man among you be wiſe, <hi>thus;</hi> he hath a ſaying to you to tell you, that this is not that which ye ſhould ſo much ſtudy and apply your ſelves to. Thoſe which profeſs themſelves Believers, and have given up their Names to Chriſt, they ſhould not judge and reckon of themſelves by ſuch matters as theſe are. Though ſo long as they live in the world, they muſt, from the neceſſity of their condition, converſe in it and with it, yet this is not that which they ſhould look upon as their chiefeſt aime, or the mark whereunto they direct and order their courſe, but regard better things, and of an higher nature; Saint <hi>Paul</hi> gives us both his Precept for it, and his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample: His <hi>Precept,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Coloſſ. 3.1, 2. <hi>If then ye be riſen with Chriſt, ſeek thoſe things which are above, where Chriſt ſitteth at the right hand of God: Set your affections on things above, and not on things on the earth.</hi> And his <hi>Example, Phil.</hi> 3.20. <hi>Our converſation is in Heaven, from whence we look for the Saviour, the Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of a <hi>contrary</hi> Diſpoſition hereunto are all ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons as thoſe who give themſelves to nothing but the <hi>world,</hi> and the intereſts of it: All their thoughts, and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:166481:10"/>meditations, and deſires and affections which are in them, they run out upon this: If ye could Anatomize a carnal perſon, rip him up, and ſee what is <hi>in him,</hi> ye ſhould find the <hi>world in his heart</hi> as his chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt Good, and Treaſure and Delight, worldly Plots, worldly Policies, worldly Contrivances, all ſavouring of the world, as if he were made and created for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but to live here below, and to enjoy the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts of this preſent life. I would that this Diſtemper had been only the Diſtemper of <hi>Corinth,</hi> and confined to thoſe times wherein the Apoſtle wrote this Epiſtle; But it is not ſo, it runs down all along in a <hi>Succeſsion,</hi> even to following Generations, and ſo wil do whilſt the world it ſelf laſts. That is the firſt Explication of the wiſdom of the world, conſidered more Generally and at Large in the common notion of it, <hi>Sapientia Mundi.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond is <hi>Sapientia Seculi:</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. The wiſdom of the Age.</note> The Wiſdome of the <hi>Age.</hi> Not only of <hi>the world,</hi> but of <hi>this world;</hi> that is, this <hi>moment</hi> of the world in which we live: As the world in general has its defilements of worldly wiſdome adhering to it, ſo every point and eſtate of the world hath ſome particularity or other of this worldly wiſdome in it, as a Branch or ſlip of that Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, which does run out and expreſs it ſelf in ſeveral Ages and times of it, and for the moſt part one worſe then another. <hi>Aetas parentum pejor avis.</hi> Now this is that likewiſe which is here implicitely cenſured by the Apoſtle in this Expreſſion: If any among you be wiſe in <hi>this world,</hi> that is, wiſe with the ſubtilties and miſcarriages of this <hi>preſent Age.</hi> Hence we read of the <hi>faſhion</hi> of this world [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.13. The ſhape, or form, or appearance. And of the <hi>courſe</hi> of this world, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.2.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:166481:11"/>And of the <hi>luſt</hi> of this world, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.17. So 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.10. <hi>Demas</hi> hath forſaken me, and imbraced this <hi>preſent world:</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, The world, and the world that <hi>now is.</hi> And that he might deliver us from this <hi>preſent evil world,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Galat.</hi> 1.4. Every Age and Time of the world, it has its particular Corruptions and Extravagancies both in matter of Judgment and Practice, which are redundant in it. There are the <hi>Errors</hi> of the Times on <hi>one hand,</hi> and there are the <hi>Vanities</hi> of the Times on another; and men are then ſaid to be wiſe in either of them, when they do cloſe and comply with them, and ſute and conform unto them. And ſo now you have the firſt particular, as a part of the Apoſtles cenſure in this reſpect, <hi>viz</hi> a Miſtake of Falſe wiſdome for True, or of that which is leſs conſiderable, for that which is more; which you have had in a threefold Explicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on laid open to you: In the Wiſdom of the <hi>Mind, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural</hi> Wiſdome: in the Wiſdom of the <hi>Fleſh, Carnal</hi> Wiſdom: in the Wiſdom of the <hi>VVorld, Secular</hi> Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</p>
            <p>The ſecond thing which he here cenſures is the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence to true Wiſdome,<note place="margin">II. The meer pretence to Wiſdom.</note> in the want of it; <hi>That</hi> you have in the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, if any man <hi>ſeems:</hi> It is not, If any man <hi>be</hi> wiſe; but if he <hi>ſeem</hi> to be. In which expreſsion, as the Apoſtle doth implicitely caſt a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach upon the Wiſdom of the World it ſelf, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch only in <hi>appearance,</hi> and not in <hi>reality,</hi> which things have a <hi>ſhew</hi> of wiſdom, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.23. So he does caſt a reproach likewiſe upon thoſe which are preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to it, as making ſhew and profeſſion of more wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom then is indeed in them, ſuch as <hi>ſeem</hi> wiſe, but <hi>are</hi> not ſo. This is that which wee find by the Apoſtle
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:166481:11"/>
               <hi>Paul</hi> in another place to be laid to the charge of the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles</hi> and Heathen Philoſophers,<note place="margin">Rom. 1.22.</note> 
               <hi>That profeſsing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be wiſe, they became fools. Wiſdome</hi> was that which they pretended to; but <hi>Folly</hi> was that which was moſt obſervable and remarkable in them: This is the caſe of many more beſides: All that Wiſdome which they ſeem to lay claim to as their intereſt and belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unto them, if it be brought to a juſt tryal and exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation and diſcovery of it, it will at laſt prove to be no better then <hi>Folly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third and laſt part of this Cenſure extends it ſelf to <hi>Self-conceitedneſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">III. Pride in wiſdom.</note> and Pride, and vain applauding of themſelves in that Wiſdom which they conceive to be in them. If any man ſeems, that is, ſeem to <hi>him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf,</hi> and <hi>to his own mind,</hi> and fancy, and imagination<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Juſtin Martyr. ad Zen. &amp; Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren. Epiſtola. So alſo the <hi>Syr. &amp; Arab.</hi>
               </note>; ſo ſome Tranſlations carry it, and expreſs it, <hi>Si quis</hi> ſibi <hi>videtur ſapiens.</hi> This was that which theſe <hi>Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> were eſpecially guiltie of: They were wiſe men, and they did too much <hi>pride</hi> themſelves in their wiſdom, and were <hi>lifted up</hi> with it: now the Apoſtle does very ſeaſonably ſet himſelf againſt ſuch an humour as this, as the Spirit of God does likewiſe in other places of Scripture beſides this, Prov. 3.7. <hi>Be not wiſe in thine own eyes, fear the Lord, &amp;c.</hi> So Rom. 12.16. <hi>Be not wiſe in your own conceits:</hi> And Iſai. 5.21. <hi>VVo unto them that are wiſe in their own eyes, and prudent in their owne ſight.</hi> Again, Prov. 26.12. <hi>Seeſt thou a man wiſe in his own conceit? there is more hope of a fool then of him.</hi> Thus is this <hi>Self-applauſe</hi> in Wiſdome every where al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt cryed out upon,<note place="margin">Qui ſeiplum habet pro ſapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ente, Eum ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent Deus &amp; Homines pro ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naro. <hi>Arab. Adag.</hi>
               </note> according to that ſaying of the <hi>Arabians,</hi> which is frequent amongſt them, <hi>He that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts himſelf for a wiſe man, God and men account him for a fool.</hi> And Saint <hi>Paul</hi> to the like purpoſe, elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:166481:12"/>1 Cor. 8.2. <hi>If any man think that he knoweth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing, he knoweth nothing yet as he ought to know.</hi> And thus much may ſuffice of this firſt Branch in this ſecond General; <hi>viz. The Perſon ſpoken to,</hi> or implicitely cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured by the Apoſtle; <hi>If any man among you ſeemeth to be wiſe in this world:</hi> where the Cenſure reaches and extends it ſelf to theſe Particulars: 1. The Miſtake of Wiſdom. 2. The meer pretence to it. 3. The Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in it.</p>
            <p>The Second Branch is the <hi>Counſel</hi> it ſelfe,<note place="margin">The ſecond branch of the <hi>2<hi rend="sup">d</hi>
                  </hi> General, The Advice which is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, [<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> in theſe words, <hi>Let him become a Fool.</hi> This will require a little Explication in what ſenſe it is to be taken by us here in this place; which we ſhall the better underſtand by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flecting upon that which before was ſaid to be <hi>Wiſdom:</hi> Accordingly as we there underſtand being <hi>wiſe in this world;</hi> in a proportion hereunto are we to underſtand this <hi>becoming a Fool:</hi> Now this (as we may remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber) was reduced to three Heads, which I muſt now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain here bring to your thoughts, though ſomewhat inverting the order of them. Firſt, The Wiſdom of the Fleſh, Carnal, or Divelliſh Wiſdom. Secondly, The Wiſdom of the World, Earthly or Secular Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. Thirdly, The Wiſdom of the Mind, Natural or Humane Wiſdom. Now to <hi>become a Fool,</hi> is in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the <hi>two former</hi> to be in a ſtate of direct oppoſition againſt them, and contrarietie to them: in regard of the latter, to be ſo only by way of <hi>Interpretation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We begin with the former;<note place="margin">I. In oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to carnall wiſdom.</note> and here the firſt of them which I have now named is <hi>Carnal,</hi> or <hi>Divelliſh wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, The wiſdom of the Fleſh: Here</hi> now to become a Fool, is to be at the greateſt <hi>Diſtance and Separation</hi> from this that may be: Thus <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.19. I would have you <hi>wiſe unto that which is good,</hi> and <hi>ſimple concerning e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill.</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:166481:12"/>And there is another Expreſſion like unto it, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.20. In malice, be you <hi>children;</hi> though in under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding <hi>perfect men.</hi> To be a Fool, as to matter of ſin, is the higheſt Craft and Wiſdom that is, and ſo to be eſteemed: To bungle and falter here, is to ſhew the greateſt skil that may be; which therefore we ſhould all ſtudy and endeavour our ſelves unto. There are many ſad wretches in the world which have nothing to glory in but their ſhame, and what is matter of reproach unto them; that they are <hi>skilful in wickedneſs:</hi> but alas, this is but a poore matter to pride themſelves in: Why boaſteſt thou thy ſelfe in <hi>Miſchief,</hi> O mighty man! <hi>Pſal.</hi> 52.1. It were better here to have no wiſdom or skil at all. If any man in <hi>this ſenſe</hi> be wiſe, let him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a fool indeed, that ſo he may be wiſe in good ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt.</p>
            <p>Yea (which is pertinent hereunto likewiſe) let him become a fool in the <hi>opinion</hi> of the vile and wicked world, which are ready <hi>ſo to</hi> eſteem him.<note place="margin">A Fool in the opinion of the world.</note> Carnal and naughty perſons, they are ready to ſcoffe at any which have any ſavour of goodneſs in them, and to cry them down for a <hi>company of fools</hi> and witleſs perſons, as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane <hi>Michol</hi> did her Godly and Religious <hi>David,</hi> when <hi>he danced before the Ark with all his might:</hi> it is ſaid, <hi>She deſpiſed him in her heart,</hi> 2 Sam. 6.16. And ſhe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt it alſo with her tongue, <hi>ver.</hi> 20. of the ſame chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. <hi>How glorious was the King of Iſrael to day, who like a Fool uncovered himſelf, &amp;c.</hi> But how does he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer her again? I will be <hi>yet more vile then thus,</hi> and <hi>will be baſe in mine own ſight,</hi> &amp;c. As who ſhould ſay, If <hi>this</hi> be to be a fool, I am reſolved to be a fool ſtil; which I look upon as an high piece of Dignity and glory to me. Thus then here in the Text, <hi>Let him become a fool,</hi> it is
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:166481:13"/>to be taken by us, not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ſecundùm Opinionem Vulgi,</hi> as men count Folly. As the world and the men of the world eſteem of it, ſo let him that is <hi>wiſe as to matter of wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs,</hi> become a <hi>fool, For if we be beſides our ſelves, it is to God,</hi> 2 Cor. 5.13. And who then would not be beſides himſelf ſo, even to chuſe, rather any thing elſe? <hi>Stultus fiat</hi> (ſaith <hi>Aquinas</hi>) <hi>abjiciendo iſtam ſapientiam apparen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem, ut ſit ſapiens ſecundùm ſapientiam Divìnam, quae eſt vera ſapientia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is ſo far the ſenſe of the Text, as that ſome have <hi>ſo</hi> read the words by pointing them thus, <hi>If any man a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you ſeem to be wiſe;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>in this world let him become a fool;</hi> that is, a fool in the <hi>opinion</hi> of this world, which will be ready ſo to reckon him, when he applies himſelf to the trueſt Wiſdom. Thus we ſee how it holds in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to <hi>carnal</hi> wiſdom.</p>
            <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">II. In oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wiſdom.</note> Take it in oppoſition to <hi>worldly</hi> wiſdom: Let him become a fool even ſo likewiſe; that is, as leſs ſpending his time in <hi>worldly matters,</hi> and making <hi>them</hi> his chiefeſt buſineſs and imployment: it does not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a Chriſtian to be thus, <hi>Like Martha, troubled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout many things;</hi> to be <hi>nimis attentus ad rem,</hi> given to the imbracements of the world, in the Riches, and Pleaſures, and Faſhions, and Vanities of it; but to keep himſelf here <hi>unſpotted</hi> as much as may be.</p>
            <p>Thirdly,<note place="margin">III. In the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lification of naturall wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</note> Let him become a fool; it may be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood likewiſe with a reference to <hi>Natural</hi> Wiſdom: That Wiſdom which conſiſts in Parts, and Learning, and Humane Knowledg. And here now to become a fool is not to be taken as it was in the former, by way of <hi>Negation</hi> and <hi>Oppoſition,</hi> as if the Apoſtle did require thoſe which had ſuch perfections as theſe in them to <hi>caſt,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:166481:13"/>them off,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Oe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum. &amp; Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phylact. ex Curyſoſt. <hi>Stultus ſit Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntate, non Naturà.</hi> P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſius.</note> and to <hi>lay them aſide</hi> from them (for that had been contrary even to his <hi>own practice</hi>): But to <hi>become a fool</hi> here, is to be taken <hi>Interpretativè &amp; oeconomicè,</hi> by way of ſpecial <hi>qualification and diſpenſation:</hi> This Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly will do no body hurt that hath it, but rather the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary. As <hi>death</hi> to the world is <hi>life,</hi> ſo <hi>folly</hi> to the world is <hi>wiſdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus it may be further laid open,<note place="margin">I. A Fool; <hi>in a ſenſe of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility.</hi>
               </note> according to theſe following Explications: Firſt, By taking it in a ſenſe of <hi>Humility.</hi> A Fool, as to his <hi>owne Apprehenſions, and high flown Conceits of himſelf; therein</hi> he muſt be a Fool, though otherwiſe never ſo wiſe. And ſo the <hi>Arabick</hi> Tranſlation expreſſes it directly, even in the Text, ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring it thus, <hi>Let him become a fool as to himſelf.</hi> There is no Fault in <hi>Humane wiſdome;</hi> but there may be a Fault adherent to the <hi>Perſon</hi> which is he Subject of it, when as occaſionally from it he ſhall ſwell and exalt himſelf in it. When Knowledg ſhall at any time puffe up, and make a man proud, here now, as wee take it <hi>in concreto,</hi> it is a matter of ſome diſparagement, which accordingly is to be heeded unto, and the Apoſtles counſel is here very ſeaſonable, <hi>Let him become a fool;</hi> that is, Let him no more glory or boaſt himſelf in this perfection then as if he <hi>were a fool</hi> indeed. The Learnedſt and Wiſeſt man that is, ought to be as low, and humble, and meek in his own apprehenſions, as if he had no Wit or Learning at all in him, but were the verieſt Fool and Dunce in the world. It is the Determination this of<note n="f" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> &amp;c. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> &amp;c. Baſil. Mag. Reg. Brev. in reſp. ad Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rog. 274.</note> 
               <hi>Baſilius Caeſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reenſis,</hi> who putting this to the Queſtion, <hi>How a man may be ſaid to be a fool in this world?</hi> Gives this anſwer to it, <hi>If he be afraid of the Judgement of the Lord, who hath ſaid,</hi> Wo unto them that are wiſe in their own eyes, and prudent in their own ſight, <hi>and imitate him that hath
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:166481:14"/>ſaid, I am as a Beaſt before thee: and laying aſide all opinion of his own wiſdome, approve of nothing as right in him any further, than as well-pleaſing to God.</hi> Thus <hi>He.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. In a ſenſe of Modeſty.</note> by taking it in a ſenſe of <hi>Modeſty. Let him be a fool;</hi> i. e. <hi>content</hi> to be a fool: namely, as to <hi>prying in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſecrets and Counſels of God,</hi> which he has lockt up in his own Boſome. <hi>Great VVits</hi> they are for the moſt part full of <hi>curioſitie;</hi> they are ſubject now and then <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to <hi>ſtretch beyond their meaſure,</hi> and to go be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond their line; they which are <hi>wiſe already,</hi> they would be more wiſe than <hi>they ſhould be,</hi> and be carryed above <hi>their reach.</hi> Now the Apoſtle here by this expreſſion does correct this extravagancy in them, and reduces them to their Line and Rule, that in this ſenſe they become as fools; to wit, as being willingly ignorant of thoſe things which belong not unto them,<note place="margin">Pſal. 131.1. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> but are <hi>too high for them;</hi> which he expreſſes alſo very elegantly in another Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, <hi>Not to be wiſe above that which we ought, but to be wiſe with ſobriety,</hi> &amp;c, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.3.</p>
            <p>But <hi>thirdly,</hi>
               <note place="margin">3. In a ſenſe of Self-denial.</note> (and indeed chiefly) <hi>Let him become a fool,</hi> in a ſenſe of <hi>Self-denyal:</hi> A fool as to the <hi>owning</hi> of that Natural wiſdom which is truly in him: ſo as thereby to be kept off from the imbracement of the <hi>Doctrine of the Goſpel, and Chriſtian Religion.</hi> This ſenſe doth beſt ſuit with the ſcope of the place, and the Argument which the Apoſtle takes upon him in the beginning of this Epiſtle, which is to meet with the pride of thoſe <hi>wiſe and learned Greeks,</hi> who did therefore ſcorn the Truths of Chriſt, as not complying with their <hi>humane Reaſon;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chryſoſt. in loc.</note> So <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> undrſtands it: <hi>He</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is a fool to the world,</hi> who ſlights the wiſdom of the world, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>as to the comprehenſion of the Doctrines of Faith.</hi> To ſuch as theſe the Apoſtle
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:166481:14"/>here turns and directs his ſpeech, that if there were any ſuch amongſt them who were wiſe in a <hi>way of parts,</hi> and natural underſtanding, they ſhould not abſolutely <hi>caſt them away,</hi> but <hi>veil</hi> them to the wiſdom of Chriſt. This is the meaning of the text; He that will be <hi>wiſe to God,</hi> muſt be thus far a <hi>fool to Himſelf:</hi> he muſt beleeve more then his <hi>Reaſon</hi> and ſhallow Underſtanding is able to fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thom and comprehend. Look, as in <hi>Providential Truths</hi> and matters of <hi>Divine Promiſe,</hi> we muſt beleeve beyond <hi>Senſe and outward Appearance;</hi> ſo likewiſe in <hi>Theologi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Truths</hi> and matters of Divine <hi>Propoſition,</hi> wee muſt beleeve beyond <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>inward Apprehenſion:</hi> And he that will not be a fool <hi>thus</hi> he is a fool <hi>already.</hi> This is the nature of the Goſpel, as the Apoſtle ſpeaks of it, that the <hi>weapons of it are not carnall, but mighty through God, to the pulling down of ſtrong holds, Caſting down i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maginations,</hi> or <hi>reaſonings,</hi> [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] <hi>and every high thing that exalts it ſelf againſt the knowledg of God; and bringing into captivity every thought to the obedience of Chriſt:</hi> To the obedience of Chriſt, that is, to <hi>yeeld o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience unto Chriſt.</hi> And obedience not onely <hi>practicall,</hi> the obedience of <hi>works,</hi> for the <hi>doing</hi> of that which Chriſt impoſes upon us: but obedience alſo which is <hi>mentall,</hi> or <hi>cordiall,</hi> the obedience of <hi>Faith;</hi> for the <hi>beleeving and cloſing</hi> with that which Chriſt propounds unto us. The Spirit of Chriſt in the Goſpel hath this prevalency and efficacy with it, as to bring the higheſt thoughts that are, into this ſubjection: and ſo we muſt be content to have it, without wrangling or quarrelling againſt it. The proud heart of man is in this caſe loth to ſtoop: but it muſt <hi>for all that,</hi> if ever it will be that which it ſhould be; and it is that which is here intimated by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle <hi>Paul</hi> in this preſent Text, <hi>If any man among you,</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:166481:15"/>&amp;c. But of this I ſhall have occaſion to ſpeak more af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward, out of the laſt General; and therefore ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frain it here. So much of the Counſel, or Exhortation exhibited, <hi>Let him become a fool.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next is in order to what this Counſel or Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation is given;<note place="margin">The third branch of the <hi>3<hi rend="sup">d</hi>
                  </hi> Generall. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> the <hi>End</hi> and Scope of it: and that is, <hi>That he may be wiſe.</hi> It is well this is added to the other: If the Apoſtle had ſaid, <hi>Let him become a fool,</hi> and had ſtopt <hi>there,</hi> it might have ſeemed ſomewhat ſtrange; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, had leſs efficacy with it. Now whiles he ſub-joynes this further: <hi>That he may be wiſe.</hi> He takes off all ſcruple from it. That's a good folly which at laſt ends in wiſdom, as the proper and natural Effect and Conſequent of it.<note place="margin">Here 2 things more:
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The</hi> End it ſelf.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The</hi> Means unto it.</item>
                  </list>
               </note> There are two things which are here pertinently conſiderable, the one is the end it ſelf ſimply propound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and the other is the connexion of this end, with the means leading and tending to it.</p>
            <p>For the firſt,<note place="margin">1. The End it ſelf, <hi>Wiſdome.</hi>
               </note> The end here propounded to the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians,</hi> and in them to all of us, <hi>It is wiſdom:</hi> But in a <hi>Spiritual and Supernatural</hi> acception. To be wiſe to <hi>God,</hi> to be wiſe to Eternity, to be wiſe to ſalvation, to be wiſe for the good and welfare of our own precious and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal ſouls: this is the wiſdome here ſpoken of, as a Prize which is worth the ſeeking and looking after. And indeed (to ſpeak of) there is no other wiſdome but this. What the Philoſopher ſpoke of <hi>Wiſdome and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> in his <hi>Politick and Moral</hi> Conſideration, is more e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially true of it in our <hi>Spiritual; It is impoſsible for him to be a Wiſe-man, that is not a Good-man</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Ariſt. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thic. l. 6. c. 13.</note>. This is that which every one ſhould aym at eſpecially, above any thing elſe. <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> (as <hi>Salomon</hi> tells us, and he means it of <hi>Grace</hi>) it is the <hi>Principal thing; therefore we muſt get wiſdom,</hi> and in all <hi>our gettings, get this underſtanding,</hi> Pro. 4.7.</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:166481:15"/>
            <p>What does this Wiſdom conſiſt in?<note place="margin">Wherein this wiſdome does conſiſt. 1. Sight of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural miſery. 2. Apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Chriſt.</note> Briefly in theſe particulars. Firſt, In the ſight and apprehenſion of our own naturall miſery, and corruption, and folly, together with the ſleights and ſubtilties of Satan our ſpiritual Enemy, to improve them. Secondly, In the diſcerning of he ſufficiency and excellencie which is in Chriſt, and the Knowledg of Him; when we have that beſtowed upon us, which the Apoſtle praies for concerning the Epeſians;<note place="margin">Epheſ. 1.17.</note> 
               <hi>The ſpirit of Wiſdome, and Revelation in the Knowledg of Chriſt.</hi> And then Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, beſides this work upon <hi>the Underſtanding,</hi>
               <note place="margin">3. Cloſing with Chriſt.</note> an incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the <hi>Will and Affections</hi> ſutable hereunto, whereby this wiſdom becomes not onely <hi>Notional,</hi> but <hi>Practical;</hi> our <hi>hearts</hi> being proportionably ſanctified and fill'd with it, and our <hi>lives and converſations</hi> receiving the like tincture from our hearts.</p>
            <p>There are divers Arguments which I might preſs to the purſuit of it, but I cannot now inſiſt upon them;<note place="margin">Motives per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwading to it. 1. The Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency. 2. The Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit. 3. The Digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty or Renown.</note> 1. The <hi>Excellency</hi> of it, it is wiſdome of the higheſt nature. 2. The <hi>Benefit</hi> of it, it is wiſdome that will ſtand us moſt in ſtead, and which will be moſt uſeful to us. 3. The <hi>Dignity</hi> of it, it carryes the greateſt Honour, and Renown, and Credit with it; all theſe are conſiderable in it.</p>
            <p>But all which I will do now,<note place="margin">An Uſe of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination.</note> ſhall be onely to call you to an <hi>inquiry</hi> about your own intereſt in it. <hi>Wiſdome</hi> is that which every one almoſt pretends to, and <hi>Spiritual</hi> wiſdom too: But it is not ſuch as every <hi>one hath,</hi> or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed partakes of. Would you know for your own par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, whether <hi>you</hi> do ſo or no? Would ye ſhew it, and evidence it, and demonſtrate it, that in truth ye do ſo? I ſhall need to give you no other diſcovery, than that of the Apoſtle <hi>James,</hi> in that eminent place of his
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:166481:16"/>to this purpoſe, <hi>Jam.</hi> 3.13, &amp;c. <hi>Who is a wiſe man, and indued with knowledge amongſt you? Let him ſhew out of a good Converſation his works with meekneſs of wiſdome. But if ye have bitter envying and ſtrife in your hearts, glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry not, and lye not againſt the Truth. This wiſdome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendeth not from above, but is earthly, ſenſual, and diveliſh: For where envying and ſtrife is, there is confuſion and every evil work. But the wiſdom that is from above, is firſt pure, then peaceable, gentle, and eaſie to be intreated, full of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and good fruits, without partiality, and without Hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie. And the fruit of Righteouſneſſe is ſown in peace, of them that make peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Text, it is very pregnant, and ſignificant, and full of Emphaſis, and ſuch as I deſire in a ſpecial manner to commend unto you, and leave with you, as a good Comment upon this which I have now taken to handle amongſt you; it is ſuch as would be well thought of ſometimes by you, even then when ye are <hi>ſomewhere elſe</hi> beſides in this place, and are otherwiſe imploy'd: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to conſider how farre you expreſs this wiſdome here ſpoken of, or degenerate from it; you ſee the Apoſtle ſets it in the way of a double deſcription, that we may the better take notice of it. In the Negative, and in the Poſitive, and both of them very ſeaſonably conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable of us. For which purpoſe it is not amiſs for us to take a brief view and account of the whole Scripture it ſelf, as it lies before us. The Apoſtles ſcope in the fore going part of the Chapter, was to reſtrain the exor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitancies of the Tongue which he does amplifie and ſet forth by many ſingular and ſpecial illuſtrations: Now this, becauſe it does (for the moſt part) proceed from pride and haughtineſs of ſpirit, and this pride does alſo commonly ariſe from a conceit, and falſe perſwaſion of
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:166481:16"/>mens own wiſdome, that they (forſooth) are a great deal wiſer than any body elſe; therefore does he here alſo deſcend to treat of true wiſdome it ſelf, and to ſhew the properties of it, <hi>Who is a wiſe man,</hi> &amp;c. As if he had ſaid,<note place="margin">Jam. 3.13 <hi>ad finem Cap.</hi> pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raphraſed.</note> 
               <q>There are a great many of you, which go for wiſe men, and ſuch as are in dued with ſpecial gifts of knowledge farre above others; now it is not enough for you, that ye have the name and profeſſion of it upon you, it will concern you to ſhew it, and make it good in the thing it ſelf. This ye cannot do better, than by a converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſutable to ſuch Principles, which may produce the works of meekneſs, and ſweetneſs, and quietneſs, and peaceableneſs in you, which are the effects of true wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome indeed; whereas, if ye allow your ſelves in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary diſtempers of envy, and ſtrife, and emulation, and contention, and the like; howſoever ye may haply pleaſe and applaud your ſelves in ſuch courſes as thoſe are, yet you are exceedingly ſhort of the mark, and of that wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome which ye falſly attribute and aſſume to your ſelves. There is no ſhadow of wiſdom in it, except it be of that, which deſerves not the name of wiſdome, the wiſdome of the World, and the wiſdome of the Fleſh, and the wiſdome of the Divel: Foe where ſuch paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and humors as theſe are do at any time take place, ther's nothing but tumults, and turbulency, and diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and confuſion, and every evil; work which are in the greateſt oppoſition to true wiſdome, that poſſibly can be. Which that ye may know to be ſo indeed, I will give you a ſhort Deſcription of this wiſdome what it is: That wiſdome which comes from above, (which I ſuppoſe is that you pretend to, and deſire to have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in you) it is in the firſt place Pure and Holy, that is, clean from any eminent vice in him which is the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:166481:17"/>of it. Then peaceable, that is, full of tranquilli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and calmneſs of ſpirit.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> After that, gentle and eaſie to be intreated; that is, not ſelfiſh or too much addict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to ones own judgment, and opinion, and reſolution; but where there is ground and reaſon for it (and in ſuch things as are lawful and honeſt) plyable to the wills and underſtandings of other men. Without <hi>partiality</hi> (ſay ſome) that is, making no difference of perſons, ſo as to eſteem or contemn any for carnal reſpects: With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>wrangling</hi> (ſay others) as that which does proceed from the envy and ſtrife before mentioned. And with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out hypocriſie, that is, the pretences of ſtanding for Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, and Piety, and Juſtice, and Religion, and the like, without cordial affection to it; and the fruit of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs is ſown in Peace of them that make Peace. Theſe two they are not inconſiſtent or oppoſite one to the other. If any pretend to this, that they ſtand for Righteouſneſs, this he tells them, that ſo they may, and for quietneſs too both at once. Ther's no neceſſity for it, that whiles they ſtand up for Juſtice, they ſhould withdraw from Peace, for they both agree very well together,<note place="margin">Pſal. 85.10.</note> 
                  <hi>Mercy and Truth may meet together, Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Peace may kiſs each other.</hi>]</q> Thus, as briefly as I could, have I opened this Scripture to you, as a Diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of True and Right Wiſdom, and (as I ſaid) leave it with you. And ſo much of the firſt Point, to wit, the <hi>End</hi> here propounded, which is wiſdom it ſelf; That he may <hi>be wiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now in the ſecond place,<note place="margin">2. The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexion of the End with the Means.</note> it is worth our obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the <hi>Connexion of this End</hi> with the <hi>Means</hi> tending to it, by reflecting and turning back upon the words before, <hi>Let him become a fool.</hi> This is a ſtrange Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexion in the firſt Repreſentation of it: To become a
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:166481:17"/>
               <hi>Fool</hi> that one may be made a <hi>wiſe Man:</hi> Yet thus it is:<note place="margin">Folly the way to wiſdom.</note> We ſee here how Religion has its ſeeming Contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Inconſiſtencies in it. <hi>Gods wayes</hi> are not as <hi>our wayes,</hi> nor <hi>His Thoughts</hi> as <hi>our Thoughts,</hi> as Himſelfe hath expreſt it <hi>Iſai.</hi> 55.8. With <hi>Him,</hi> Folly is the high-way to Wiſdom it ſelf, and leads unto it. When he once makes us Chriſtians, he takes a quite contrary courſe with us then hath been hitherto taken: As that Philoſopher did with his Scholers, he teaches us firſt <hi>forgetfulneſs</hi> of whatſoever we have learnt in the School of <hi>Vanity</hi> and <hi>Sin.</hi> We muſt (when we come to him to be taught by him) let go all our former Principles which were ſettled in us: There are many that <hi>imagine otherwiſe,</hi> think they may be wiſe to the <hi>World,</hi> and to <hi>God</hi> both at once. But it will not be: If we deſire to <hi>imbrace the one,</hi> we muſt <hi>forſake the other:</hi> If ever we will attain to <hi>Spiritual</hi> Wiſdome, we muſt renounce <hi>Carnal:</hi> We muſt come to that <hi>VViſdom</hi> by this <hi>Folly.</hi> This is the <hi>Courſe and Method</hi> which God hath appointed.</p>
            <p>And the Reaſon of it is clear,<note place="margin">The Reaſon.</note> becauſe that <hi>Corrupt Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> and <hi>Grace</hi> they are of a <hi>contrary Strain.</hi> This world in the Luſts of it, and that world which is to come, they are oppoſite, and of different Intereſts. Now look as it is with Kingdomes or States here in this world, which are of contrary Factions, he that will be Wiſe for the one, he muſt in a ſenſe be a Fool for the other, becauſe their Counſels and Intereſts, and Advantages do not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree and accord together; even ſo is it here in this buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs as concerning Earth and Heaven, Nature and Grace, this World and that which is above: Their Ingagements are different, and ſo accordingly is the Wiſdome that tends to the furtherance and promotion of either.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:166481:18"/>
            <p>Therefore this is the firſt work that is to be done in the preaching of the Word,<note place="margin">The firſt work in Preaching, what?</note> to take men off from their their own bottomes, and to ſhew them that <hi>Emptineſs</hi> and <hi>Inſufficiency</hi> which is in <hi>themſelves,</hi> that ſo they may look after that <hi>Fulneſs</hi> and All-ſufficiency which is in <hi>another,</hi> even in <hi>Chriſt himſelf;</hi> which they will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver do till the former be well evidenced and demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted unto them. This was that which ſtuck in the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macks of theſe <hi>Proud Greeks,</hi> and made them unwilling to cloſe with the Preaching of the Goſpel, and the Truths contained in it, becauſe they were unwilling to be fools, and to be taken off from adoring of that wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome which was now already in them, as it became them to be. Going about to eſtabliſh their <hi>own wiſdom,</hi> they could not ſubmit themſelves unto the <hi>Wiſdome of God. Iſidorus Peluſiota</hi> reſolves this very well in his Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to his friend <hi>Epimachus</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">'H <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. Iſid. Peluſ. li. 4. Ep. 6.</note>, who deſired of him the ſenſe of <hi>this Scripture. Hear</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>in brief what it is; The Conceit and Opinion of Proficiency is a very great Hinderance thereunto; wherefore a man muſt lay aſide all Pride and Swelling in himſelf (for ſuch was the wiſdom of the</hi> Greeks, <hi>having no ſolidity in it) that ſo he may be filled with Divine Knowledge and Inſtruction.</hi> And he ſets it out by a very lively Compariſon, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>&amp;c. For look</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>as it in the Body, if ſome windy or flatulent Humour get into the Belly, it does there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by hinder concoction; ſo Pride and Conceit, if it once prepoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs the mind, it does thereby exclude all ſound knowledg, and much impair the health of the ſoul.</hi> Thus <hi>He,</hi> a Grave and an Ancient Author. And thus much of the Second General Part of the Text, which is the <hi>Word of Counſel</hi> or Exhortation, <hi>If any man among you ſeemeth to be wiſe, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:166481:18"/>
            <p>THE Third and laſt is the Word of <hi>Inforcement</hi> or Argument to perſwade unto it, in theſe words,<note place="margin">The <hi>3<hi rend="sup">d</hi>
                  </hi> Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral.</note> 
               <hi>For the Wiſdom of the world is fooliſhneſs with God:</hi> It was ſomewhat <hi>ſtrange Counſel</hi> which was given, as we hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted before, and therefore needed a <hi>Reaſon</hi> to back it and ſet it on: and this it is. According to the common <hi>form</hi> and <hi>regularity</hi> of ſpeech, ſo it ſhould rather have been thus, <hi>The fooliſhneſs of this world is wiſdome with God.</hi> But the Apoſtles aim and intent was to <hi>depreſſe worldly wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The wiſdom of the world fooliſhneſſe with God.</note>and therefore he chuſes rather to give it in this manner of expreſſion which wee have now before us. What this wiſdom of the world is, we have formerly declared out of the foregoing paſſages of the Text: It remains now that we ſhould ſee here what is ſaid of it, and the Cenſure which is faſtned upon it, and that is this, that it is <hi>Fooliſhneſſe;</hi> not in the ſenſe of a <hi>Foole</hi> (which even the <hi>beſt wiſdom</hi> is) but in the ſenſe even of <hi>wiſdom it ſelf;</hi> its Fooliſhneſs with <hi>God:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. According to aſ double Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication.</note> This it may be ſaid to be according to a double Explication. Firſt, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe He <hi>counts</hi> it ſo: And ſecondly, Becauſe he <hi>makes</hi> it ſo It is ſo according to the <hi>Opinion</hi> and <hi>Eſtimation</hi> which he hath of it; and it is ſo according to that <hi>Event</hi> and <hi>Condition</hi> which he diſpoſes to it.</p>
            <p>Firſt, It it is ſoin his Opinion;<note place="margin">I. In his opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion.</note> he <hi>reckons</hi> and <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteems</hi> it but Fooliſhneſs. This is true of the <hi>wiſdom of the world</hi> taken in its fui Latitude and Compaſs, without any further Explication; eſpecially of that which we cal <hi>Carnal wiſdom,</hi> the wiſdom of the Fleſh. But if wee ſpeak of ſome other parts of it, namely that which is <hi>Secular</hi> or <hi>Natural,</hi> which ſeems here (as we ſhewed before) to be very much aimed at, ſo it is thus only according to theſe following Qualifications which are agreeable to it.</p>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:166481:19"/>
            <p>Firſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>1.</hi> Comparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve.</note> 
               <hi>Comparitive,</hi> being compared with that which is higher and better than it ſelf. Take the <hi>wiſdome of the world,</hi> for no more but the wiſdome <hi>of natural parts and abilities</hi> for worldly imployments, and ſo it is not <hi>foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhneſſe ſimply,</hi> no, not in the eyes <hi>of God himſelf;</hi> it is fooliſhneſs in the eyes of God, for any to <hi>think</hi> it ſo: <hi>wit, and learning, and arts,</hi> and ſuch qualification as theſe are, they are fooliſhneſs with <hi>none,</hi> but ſuch as <hi>are fools themſelves,</hi> and that know not <hi>what belongs to them.</hi> The <hi>onely wiſe God</hi> look upon them, as no other <hi>than Beams and Emanations</hi> of his own Wiſdome, which do iſſue and proceed from <hi>Himſelf</hi> in a ſpecial manner; they are the Gifts of his <hi>Spirit,</hi> which he is pleaſed to beſtow up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Men,</hi> for the good, and benefit, and comfort, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of <hi>the world,</hi> but of <hi>the Church:</hi> they are the Fruits of his <hi>Sons Aſcenſion:</hi> thoſe Largeſſes and Bounties which he let fall, and left behind him, when he went up into Heaven. All the three glorious Perſons in <hi>the Bleſſed and Sacred Trinity,</hi> they have an hand in the diſpenſation of this wiſdome,<note place="margin">2 Tim. 2.13</note> which God cannot diſallow of <hi>Abſolutely,</hi> unleſs he ſhould <hi>deny Himſelf,</hi> which He <hi>cannot do.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For a man to be a prudent Stateſman, an underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Magiſtrate, a deep Scholar, a skilful Merchant, a man wel ſeen and verſ'd in that way and place and calling wherein God hath ſet him, whether of Councel or Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, or Study, or Trade, or whatever it be, theſe abilities <hi>nakedly conſidered,</hi> have no diſparagement in them at all, but rather the <hi>contrary;</hi> it is an <hi>Honour and Commendation</hi> for every man, as much as may be, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel in his kind, though in a <hi>worldly conſideration:</hi> And we may not ſo far abuſe either our ſelves, or the Spirit of God, as to fancy and imagine otherwiſe. Theſe things in their <hi>place, and in their rank,</hi> are very Excellent, and
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:166481:19"/>ſuch as the <hi>Lord Himſelf</hi> often <hi>in Scripture</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Clem. Alex. Strom. l. 1.</note> does give the <hi>name of wiſdome</hi> unto them.</p>
            <p>But now, we ſhall compare them with greater and higher matters, <hi>here</hi> they are no better than <hi>fooliſhneſs.</hi> If we compare Wit with Grace, Learning with Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Sagacity with a ſpirit of Diſcerning, a ſtrong and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litick Brain with a Gracious and Savoury Heart; here now they are not to <hi>be named the ſame day</hi> (as I may ſay) together, ther's ſo much difference betwixt them, and the latter ſo tranſcendent to the former.</p>
            <p>This is that which the Apoſtle would ſignifie by this Expreſſion; he applyes himſelf to the <hi>preſent ſtate</hi> and condition of theſe <hi>Corinthians,</hi> and cures contraries by contraries. <hi>They</hi> were very much taken with the <hi>admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> of worldly wiſdome, and had too high a conceit of it, whereby they did alſo <hi>over-value</hi> and eſteem of <hi>themſeives:</hi> And now, that he might <hi>correct and reform</hi> this diſtemper in them, he does, by <hi>the bowing of the ſtick as it were another way,</hi> put the name of <hi>fooliſhneſſe</hi> upon it, thereby to take off their inordinate affection from it. As if, when ye ſhould ſee one that was fondly enamoured and raviſh'd with the Beauty of <hi>ſome Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> ye ſhould, to cure him of that fondnes in him, tell him, that in the eyes and judgement of all thoſe that had skill in features, this <hi>Beauty,</hi> it were no better than <hi>Defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity;</hi> even <hi>thus</hi> does Saint <hi>Paul</hi> with theſe <hi>Corinthians:</hi> And it was ſutable to the apprehenſions which himſelf had, being now converted, <hi>who counted all things but loſs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 3.8. 1 Cor. 2.3.</note> 
               <hi>for the excellency of the knowledg of Chriſt, and determined to know nothing amongſt them, ſave Jeſus Chriſt, and him crucified.</hi> To <hi>know,</hi> and <hi>to make</hi> known, there's both in it, Nothing but <hi>Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> What? Nothing <hi>abſolutely?</hi> No, but nothing <hi>comparatively:</hi> Nothing ſo <hi>much</hi> as
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:166481:20"/>this, or that, which does <hi>ſome way or other</hi> belong unto it: So <hi>He</hi> deſired to know, and to make known nothing elſe.</p>
            <p>This is ſo much the more remarkable, as it comes from ſuch a <hi>kind of Perſon</hi> as <hi>the Apoſtle himſelf;</hi> which was a man as <hi>eminent</hi> for that which he <hi>ſpake againſt,</hi> as any that he ſpake unto, and a great <hi>deal more.</hi> For a <hi>fool</hi> to ſpeak ſlightly of wiſdome, it may be (perhaps) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he <hi>wants</hi> it, and is deſtitute of it (as thoſe who want any excellency or perfection <hi>themſelves,</hi> they are apt to diſparage it in <hi>other:</hi>) But for the <hi>Apoſtle Paul</hi> to do it, who was ſo famous and admirable for it, one <hi>that had ſate at the feet of Gamaliel,</hi> and <hi>ſpake with Tongues more then them all,</hi> an <hi>accurate and complete Scholar</hi> in all kind of Learning, this proceeded from an <hi>Higher Principle,</hi> which was <hi>moreover and beſides</hi> in him, which made him to look upon the other, as ſo much inferior. And that's the firſt qualification. <hi>The wiſdome of the World, is fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe with God,</hi> taken <hi>comparatively.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>2.</hi> Solitariè.</note> Taken <hi>ſolitarily</hi> and alone by it ſelf. Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural or ſecular wiſdome is ſuch, as may be good within <hi>its compaſſe;</hi> but it is not good for us to have <hi>no other</hi> wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome <hi>in</hi> us but onely <hi>this.</hi> As ye ſhall obſerve it ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to be the condition of abundance of people, that take them (it may be) at ſome <hi>Bargain,</hi> or Purchaſe, or Conveyance, or <hi>worldly contrivances,</hi> here they <hi>are old excellent,</hi> in their ſphere and proper Element: But bring them to any matter of <hi>Religion,</hi> and here they are to ſeek, and not able to ſay any thing to it. There are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny which are of admirable parts for any thing which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs <hi>to the world;</hi> which yet in <hi>the wayes of God</hi> are abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute <hi>Dunces.</hi> Religion is a buſineſs which they do not much <hi>regard,</hi> or trouble themſelves with; <hi>God</hi> is not in all their <hi>thoughts;</hi> or if he be it is in ſuch a <hi>notion of him,</hi>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:166481:20"/>as is almoſt a good as none at all. There are many <hi>Chriſtians</hi> which have no other thoughts of God then if they were <hi>Heathens;</hi> look upon him only as a <hi>Creator,</hi> as the <hi>Maker</hi> and <hi>Governor</hi> of the world, and that is all, (as any of the <hi>ancient Philoſophers</hi> would have look'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him:) But as he has revealed <hi>himſelf in his Son,</hi> and has made known himſelf in the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> here they care not for him, nor apply themſelves to him: Now this is that which the Apoſtle does here condemn. Even Godlineſs it ſelf is <hi>Fooliſhneſs,</hi> if you take it <hi>abſtracted from Chriſt,</hi> eſpecially in the <hi>Church</hi> of Chriſt, where it is his maine deſign to be advanced and ſet up by us. That where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in God himſelf would manifeſt his <hi>greateſt Wiſdom, viz.</hi> the <hi>Extolling of Chriſt,</hi> in the contrary thereunto do men manifeſt their <hi>greateſt Folly, viz.</hi> by diminiſhing <hi>from Chriſt.</hi> Thus did many of <hi>theſe Greeks</hi> which Saint <hi>Paul</hi> here reflects upon, and cenſures them for it; theſe <hi>Corinthians</hi> they had divers amongſt them which were great Philoſophers, Underſtanding Merchants, elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent and well ſpoken men, which had the command of their tongue and Language, but all this while they were to ſeek in the <hi>knowledg and wiſdom of Chriſt;</hi> the <hi>Goſpel</hi> it was <hi>Fooliſhneſs</hi> unto them: Now, is not this extreme fondneſs and fooliſhneſs in good earneſt; for men to be wiſe in any thing rather then in that which they ſhould be? or which does more <hi>chiefly</hi> and <hi>principally</hi> concern them? To be wiſe to get Money, and to get Lands, and to get Eſtates, and ſuch things as theſe, and not to be wiſe to get an intereſt in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and an inheritance in a better world? To be wiſe to <hi>loſe</hi> their ſouls, and not to be wiſe to <hi>ſave</hi> them? this, it is Fooliſhneſs <hi>with a witneſs.</hi> And that's alſo the ſecond Explication, <hi>Sapientia Mundi,</hi> i.e. <hi>Sapientia quae</hi> ſola <hi>eſt Mundi.</hi> The worlds wiſdom is fool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhneſs
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:166481:21"/>with God, ſo far forth as it hath not his <hi>own</hi> wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom annexed unto it and joined with it, taken <hi>Solitarily</hi> and alone by it <hi>ſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>3.</hi> Abuſivè.</note> the Wiſdom of the world is Fooliſhneſs with God in the <hi>Abuſe</hi> and <hi>Miſ-improvement</hi> of it: <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pientia Mundi,</hi> i. e. <hi>Sapientia qua</hi> utitur <hi>mundus:</hi> The <hi>worlds wiſdom,</hi> as it is for the moſt part <hi>carried</hi> by the world, to Pride and Scorn, and Contempt, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dervaluing of the Goſpel and Miniſtry of it. When men are ſo fully poſſeſt with their worldly wiſdom, as that they deſpiſe the poor Servants of Chriſt, which in ſuch matters are inferior to them: here God looks upon it as no better then Folly. Theſe natural perfections which we have now ſpoken of, its not Fooliſhneſs to <hi>have</hi> them, but it is Fooliſhneſs to be <hi>puft up</hi> with them; and from thence to contemn others which are ſimply deſtitute of them. There is no man that has any of theſe things in the greateſt meaſure that can be, who has any reaſon to ſwell in himſelf for the injoyment and participation of them; whether he conſiders how he comes by them, which is only by gift; or whether he conſiders how eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he may <hi>loſe</hi> them, and be deprived of them; or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he conſiders how they are ſuch gifts, which for the nature and quality of them may be beſtowed upon thoſe who are Reprobates, and Caſt awayes; and Enemies, and Wicked men. So that thats another Qualification of this Expreſſion, The wiſdom of the world is Fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs with God, in the <hi>abuſe and Miſ-improvement</hi> of it; more particularly as it is at any time made a Ground of <hi>Arrogancy</hi> and <hi>Carnal confidence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>4.</hi> Effectivè.</note> 
               <hi>In ordine ad talem affectum,</hi> In reference to ſuch an Effect as is here <hi>implied</hi> and to <hi>intimated</hi> to us. The <hi>wiſdom</hi> of the world is <hi>Fooliſhneſs with God;</hi> name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:166481:21"/>as to bring men to God, and acquaint them with him. In which reſpect there is an Inſufficiency in it; and this according to a twofold Explication. Firſt,<note place="margin">A double In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficiency in worldly wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</note> An Inſufficiency <hi>Pasſive; In ratione Objecti.</hi> The wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of the world has not that in it by way of <hi>Motive,</hi> which might perſwade God to accept, or to make choice of it. Secondly, An Inſufficiency <hi>Active; In rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one potentiae.</hi> The wiſdom of the world has not that in it by way of <hi>Faculty,</hi> as whereby it may reach and appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend the things of God. According to either of theſe Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications may it be juſtly ſaid to be fooliſhnes with him.</p>
            <p>Firſt, I ſay, taken <hi>Pasſively,</hi> or <hi>Objectively,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>I.</hi> Paſſivè; in ratione Objecti.</note> and by way of <hi>Motive,</hi> it is Fooliſhneſs and Inſufficiency <hi>here.</hi> God does not accept of any perſons ſo far forth as they do only abound with worldly wiſdom; it is not that which he does ſo much regard and look at in them. And this again, as to a twofold purpoſe;<note place="margin">In reference to
<list>
                     <item>the Means.</item>
                     <item>the End.</item>
                  </list>
               </note> whether we take it in reference to the <hi>Means,</hi> or in reference to the <hi>End:</hi> If in reference to the <hi>Means,</hi> he does not for this beſtow his <hi>Grace and Goſpel</hi> upon them.<note place="margin">Act. 20 32,</note> If in reference to the <hi>End,</hi> he does not for this beſtow his <hi>Glory</hi> or Salvation upon them: Take it which way you wil, there is in this reſpect an <hi>inſufficiency</hi> in it.</p>
            <p>Firſt, In reference to the <hi>Means,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. In reference to the Means,</note> he does not for this beſtow upon them either his <hi>Grace</hi> or his <hi>Goſpel,</hi> which is the word of his <hi>Grace.</hi> It's Fooliſhneſs with him <hi>ſo;</hi> this <hi>worldly wiſdom,</hi> as the Scripture does abundantly inform us, and experience does ſometimes manifeſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us: This is clear from that ſpeech of our Saviour in his acknowledgment which he makes to his Father, Matth. 11.28. <hi>I thank thee, O Father, Lord of Heaven and earth, that thou haſt hid theſe things from the wiſe and prudent, and haſt revealed them unto Babes; even ſo,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:166481:22"/>O Father, becauſe it ſeemed good in thy ſight.</hi> And ſo 1 Cor. 1.26. <hi>You ſee your calling, brethren, how that not many wiſe men after the fleſh are called.</hi> If not many wiſe men are called, then not any are called for their <hi>wiſdom,</hi> it is not this which God has a reſpect to in his calling of them, foraſmuch as he oftentimes paſſeth by, and lets theſe alone, whilſt he faſtens upon others.</p>
            <p>There is a double undervaluing of the <hi>wiſe and pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent</hi> of the world,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Double,</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to the Means: For diſpenſing
<list>
                     <item>them to it,</item>
                     <item>them by it.</item>
                  </list>
               </note> as concerns the <hi>Means of Grace:</hi> the one is, for diſpenſing them <hi>to</hi> them; and the other is for diſpenſing them <hi>by</hi> them: and God did in either of theſe reſpects look upon the wiſdome of the world as Fooliſhneſs, and ſo accounted it.</p>
            <p>Firſt, For the diſpenſing them <hi>to</hi> them: He does not alwayes do that; nay, he does commonly other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, as we have heard out of the former place. The great <hi>Rabbies</hi> and Sophies of the world, they have been ſuch as never had the Goſpel preached unto them, or heard of the leaſt word or ſyllable of it, but have been ſuch as have <hi>ſate in darkneſſe,</hi> and in the ſhadow of death,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 2.12.</note> 
               <hi>having no hope, and without God in the world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then ſecondly, As for diſpenſing it <hi>by</hi> them. He has not alwayes done that neither; but rather taken a quite contrary courſe, as we ſee in thoſe perſons whom he firſt made choice of to ſend abroad into the world, and to lay the firſt beginnings and plantations of the Church, they were ſuch as were the greateſt ſtrangers to this worldly wiſdom of any, and which knew leaſt what belonged unto it.</p>
            <p>This is not ſo to be taken (as ſome now a dayes would improve it) as if all ſorts of perſons <hi>promiſcuouſly</hi> might take upon them the <hi>Exerciſe of the Miniſtry,</hi>
               <note place="margin">A Qualificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the truth laſt propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; by way of explication.</note> and the preaching of the Goſpel of Chriſt, though never ſo <hi>rude</hi>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:166481:22"/>and <hi>illiterate,</hi> and <hi>unqualified</hi> for ſuch a work, becauſe God made choice at firſt of a company of ſuch kind of perſons as had no ſuch kind of Learning in them. For firſt, There is a <hi>difference of time,</hi> and ſo of Gods diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſations in them. As it was in the <hi>firſt Creation</hi> of the world, all things were complete at firſt, and came up in their abſolute perfection, which yet now afterwards do not reach thereunto but by leiſure, and time, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, and the uſe of the means tending to ſuch a pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, ſowing, and planting, and watering, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuring, and the like. Even ſo was it alſo in the <hi>firſt framing of the Church:</hi> The <hi>Apoſtles</hi> they were qualified immediately by the extraordinary Endowments of the Holy Ghoſt inſpiring of them: <hi>Succeeding Miniſters</hi> they are qualified partly by ſuch <hi>Natural abilities</hi> as do much <hi>incline</hi> them to ſuch an imployment (which are ſtill the <hi>Gift of God</hi>) and partly by <hi>ſtudy and induſtry,</hi> poliſhing and further improving theſe abilities in them, with the <hi>Bleſsing of God</hi> upon them, and his <hi>Spirit</hi> in a ſpecial manner aſſiſting them in the work it ſelf, as to the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular occaſions of performance which are adminiſtred to them.</p>
            <p>Again (ſecondly) The Apoſtles they were alſo <hi>qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified;</hi> obſerve <hi>that.</hi> Though God <hi>found</hi> them under ſuch inabilities, yet he did not ſo <hi>leave</hi> them, but ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied thoſe defects in them: And though they were not men of <hi>parts</hi> when he firſt <hi>choſe</hi> them, yet they were men of <hi>Gifts</hi> when he <hi>uſed</hi> them, and ſuch Gifts as were proper to that work which he impoſed upon them. He <hi>gave Gifts</hi> to men, yea, &amp; he gave them another <hi>Call</hi> too for the exerciſe of thoſe gifts which he had given them. Therefore we may not carry this point <hi>beyond its line,</hi> which is indeed to pervert and abuſe it, and our ſelves in
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:166481:23"/>it. But only thus far, which is the Truth, that God oftentimes makes choice of <hi>men of meaner and lower parts,</hi> whom he <hi>qualifies</hi> and <hi>fits</hi> for his Miniſtry, and <hi>imployes</hi> in it, whiles he layes many others aſide of grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Natural</hi> and <hi>Secular</hi> perfections, whom he will not make uſe of; and ſo indeed he does. Thus we ſee how the Point holds good, as to <hi>Grace</hi> and the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> as the <hi>Means.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Take it further in the next place,<note place="margin">2. In reference to the End.</note> as to <hi>Glory</hi> and <hi>Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation,</hi> for the <hi>End:</hi> God does not accept of this world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Wiſdome neither in this particular. He will not bring men to Heaven, according as they have ſuch and ſuch <hi>Parts</hi> and <hi>Natural Qualifications,</hi> but rather as they have ſuch and ſuch <hi>Holy</hi> and <hi>Heavenly Diſpoſitions.</hi> He will not ſave them as having ſo much <hi>Wit,</hi> but as ſo much <hi>Grace.</hi> Wit is no further an help to Salvation, then ſo far forth as it improves <hi>Grace,</hi> and Grace <hi>it;</hi> which ſometimes it doth. That man which hath his Wiſdom ſanctified, wil be able to do a great deal more good then either one that hath ſo much Wiſdom without Sanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, or elſe, that is ſo far ſanctified without ſuch a meaſure of Wiſdom in him. Theſe things do well in their Conjunction and Connexion together, which being ſevered, do not ſo well. And ſo you have the firſt Explication, in regard whereof the Wiſdome of the World is Fooliſhneſs with God, as to <hi>Religion and the things of God;</hi> namely, from an <hi>Inſufficiency Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive</hi> conſiderable in it, <hi>In ratione Objecti,</hi> as not mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving God to accept of it, either to <hi>Grace,</hi> or elſe to <hi>Glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond is an <hi>Inſufficiency active,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>II.</hi> Activè; in ratione Poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae.</note> 
               <hi>in ratione Potentiae:</hi> The wiſdome of the world in its beſt and higheſt perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, is not able to comprehend the Truths of Chriſt.
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:166481:23"/>Meer <hi>Natural reaſon</hi> in the <hi>exacteſt ſublimation</hi> of it,<note place="margin">Naturall Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon unable to reach the things of God two manner of wayes:</note> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not reach the <hi>Doctrine of Religion;</hi> and this again it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not do according to a double ſenſe and explication of it. Firſt, Not <hi>in Propoſitione.</hi> Secondly, Not <hi>in Myſterio.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, I ſay, not alwaies in <hi>the Propoſition.</hi> There are ſome Doctrines in Religion,<note place="margin">1. <hi>In propoſitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne.</hi> Epheſ. 3.9.</note> which the <hi>Higheſt reaſon</hi> of man does not know what <hi>to make</hi> of them, neither can underſtand them as <hi>barely propounded.</hi> I do not <hi>onely ſay,</hi> that it could never <hi>find them out</hi> before they were <hi>diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered,</hi> (for <hi>that</hi> to be ſure it <hi>could not,</hi> as being meerly dependent upon <hi>the Wall and Counſel of God,</hi> and ſo ſaid to <hi>be hid in him</hi>) but that they cannot conceive of them neither <hi>fully,</hi> even now that they <hi>are revealed.</hi> Such as theſe are, <hi>the Trinity of Perſons in the Unity of Eſſence. The eternal Generation of the Son: The Proceſsion of the Holy Ghoſt: The Hypoſtatical Union of the Divine and Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Nature together.</hi> Theſe Doctrines, they are ſuch kind of Points, as do exceed and go beyond the Appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion of the higheſt <hi>Humane</hi> reaſon; ſo that the <hi>wiſdome of the world</hi> cannot reach them, or attain unto them, not ſo much as <hi>in Propoſitione.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But then ſecondly, to be ſure not <hi>in Myſterio.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>2.</hi> In Myſterio.</note> Here it cannot reach them indeed: Meer Natural reaſon, it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not diſcern the <hi>Excellency,</hi> and Beauty, and Sweeneſs of Religion: It cannot <hi>ſavour</hi> it, and <hi>reliſh</hi> it, and <hi>taſte</hi> it in the <hi>ſpirituality</hi> of it, <hi>this</hi> it cannot do; we have it plainly in the fore going Chapter, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.14. <hi>The Natural man receives not the things of the Spirit of God, for they are fooliſhneſſe to him; neither can he know them, becauſe they are Spiritually diſcerned.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Natural man,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Jude <hi>ver.</hi> 19.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> That man which hath onely a <hi>Rational ſoul</hi> in him, and no further <hi>qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> who is not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is <hi>ſpiritual;</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, He does
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:166481:24"/>not <hi>receive</hi> them, neither into his <hi>mind</hi> and judgement to <hi>underſtand</hi> them, nor into his <hi>will and affections</hi> to <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace</hi> them, and cloſe and comply with them; he does <hi>neither</hi> way receive them. This is that which muſt come from <hi>above,</hi> from the <hi>Father of lights,</hi> as every good and perfect Gift beſides; as our Saviour told <hi>Peter, Fleſh and Blood</hi> hath not revealed theſe things unto thee, but my Father which is in Heaven, <hi>Matth.</hi> 16.17. This <hi>wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God in a Myſterie,</hi> it is ſuch as the <hi>wiſeſt world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings</hi> cannot attain to: Therefore the Apoſtle ſpeaking of it, hath this paſſage concerning it, <hi>Which none of the Princes of this world knew,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 2.7, 8.</note> &amp;c. The <hi>Princes of the world?</hi> Whom does he mean by <hi>them?</hi> Not onely Princes for <hi>State,</hi> but Princes for <hi>knowledge.</hi> Not onely <hi>Kings and Emperors,</hi> but <hi>Philoſophers</hi> and <hi>Learned men,</hi> which did <hi>dominari in Scholis;</hi> Theſe are the <hi>Principes ſeculi</hi> here ſpoken of, who notwithſtanding all their Learning, and Humane wiſdome, and ſtrength of <hi>reaſon</hi> which was in them, yet did not riſe to the knowledge of Chriſt, and <hi>the Myſterie of God manifeſted in the fleſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>;<note place="margin">An uſe of Confutation.</note> (to ſpeak in the Language of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Chryſoſtome:</hi>) Where now then are thoſe, who affirm as much as this comes to, and would obtrude ſuch things as theſe upon us? which with the Greeks, <hi>ſeek after wiſdom, 1 Corinthians, Chap.</hi> 1.22. Which cry all for <hi>Reaſon,</hi> and Argument, and Demonſtration; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus</hi> calls them;<note place="margin">Strom. lib. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> and wil believe no more than they can fathom and comprehend with their own underſtanding; which would make the <hi>Truths of God</hi> ſtoop to <hi>their capacities;</hi> and bring the <hi>ſtrait line</hi> to the <hi>crooked Log?</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; (to ſpeak further in the Language of Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor,</hi> 1.20.) Where is now the <hi>VViſe?</hi> Where is the <hi>Diſputer of this world?</hi> How
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:166481:24"/>little do ſuch as theſe underſtand, or at leaſt conſider with themſelves, that the <hi>wiſdom of the world is in this reſpect fooliſhneſſe with God,</hi> who looks upon it as very ſhallow, and inferior to his Divine truth? Yea, ſo far from lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them to it, as indeed rather (in ſome kind of perſons,<note n="i" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ryſ. in 1 Tim. 1.19.</note> as in thoſe Gentiles) drawing them from it.</p>
            <p>There are many <hi>Truths in Religion,</hi> there are many <hi>Myſteries in Providence,</hi> which <hi>our Reaſon</hi> ſtaggers at; where it muſt be ſufficient for us, that <hi>God himſelf</hi> tenders them to us to be received and entertained by us; whom it is the <hi>Higheſt Reaſon</hi> to believe, even then, when the <hi>Things themſelves</hi> which we believe are <hi>Riddles and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radoxes</hi> with us.</p>
            <p>And yet we do not hereby take away mens Reaſon from them,<note place="margin">The qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> nor the uſe of it, even in Religion it ſelf. It concerns us to ſee upon what grounds we do entertain the Goſpel and Chriſtianity in the Profeſſion of it; that we do not take it up onely <hi>upon truſt,</hi> becauſe it is offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to us by <hi>men;</hi> but that we <hi>diſcern</hi> ſome excellency in it, and receive it as that which is propounded by <hi>God himſelf:</hi> Yet that we ſhould be able to ſearch into the <hi>Intrinſecal reaſon</hi> of the Doctrines and Myſteries them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, by the ſtrength of our wit, and parts, and natural underſtanding, this is not to be expected by us, or agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to us; which the Apoſtle here ſignifies to us, by this expreſſion in the Text; in calling the wiſdome of the world <hi>fooliſhneſſe:</hi> Which it is, in order to this effect, (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong other things) to wit, of <hi>bringing men to God</hi> and ſalvation. And ſo you have the firſt Explication: <hi>The wiſdome of the world is fooliſhneſſe with God;</hi> namely, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>he counts</hi> it ſo;<note place="margin">II. The wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the world, fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in Gods Diſpoſe.</note> it is ſo according to <hi>his opinion and eſtimation</hi> of it.</p>
            <p>The ſecond is, Becauſe he <hi>makes it</hi> ſo. It is ſo accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:166481:25"/>to his <hi>diſpoſal and ordering</hi> of it.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</note> Every one that <hi>counts</hi> any thing fooliſhneſs, cannot preſently <hi>make</hi> it ſo; but <hi>God</hi> can <hi>make it ſo:</hi> He <hi>hath made</hi> fooliſh the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of this world, as it is in <hi>Chap.</hi> 1. of this <hi>Epiſt. v.</hi> 20.</p>
            <p>But how does he come to do ſo? As we may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it, too manner of wayes. Firſt, by way of <hi>Fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration</hi> and <hi>Diſappointment;</hi> He ſpoiles the world of thoſe <hi>Ends and Purpoſes,</hi> which it propounds to it ſelf. Secondly, By way of <hi>Confuſion</hi> and <hi>Contrary improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;</hi> He turns their very Counſels and Deviſes againſt themſelves: In each of theſe wayes does he infatuate them.</p>
            <p>Firſt,<note place="margin">1. In a way of Fruſtration.</note> By <hi>Fruſtration</hi> and <hi>Diſappointment.</hi> God makes the wiſdome of the world fooliſhneſs thus, In that he does often croſs it of its expected ſucceſs. Thus <hi>Pſal.</hi> 35.10. <hi>The Lord bringeth the counſell of the Heathen to nought, he maketh the devices of the people of none effect.</hi> So <hi>Job</hi> 5.12. <hi>He diſappointeth the devices of the Crafty, ſo that their hand cannot perform their Enterprize.</hi> And <hi>Job</hi> 12.17. <hi>He leads away Counſellors ſpoiled, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the Judges fools.</hi> This is that which God many times does with your worldly wiſe men; he over-turns their greateſt Deſignes, <hi>and breaks them in the purpoſes of them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are many whom God ſometimes lets go on in their vain and frivolous projects, and when they are full of expectation for the ripening and perfecting of them, he does then reſtrain them in them. The Aegyptians were never more <hi>fools,</hi> than when they ſaid, <hi>Come on, let us deal wiſely, Exod.</hi> 1.10. We have a notable place for this purpoſe, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 19.11, 12, 13. &amp;c. <hi>Surely the Princes of</hi> Zoan <hi>are become fools, the counſel of the wiſe Counſellors of</hi> Pharaoh <hi>is become brutiſh. Where are they? Where are thy wiſe men?</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Let them tell thee now, and let them know
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:166481:25"/>what the Lord hath purpoſed upon</hi> Aegypt. The Lord does by theſe expreſſions ſignifie, how far he fruſtrates the Counſels of the wiſe, and prudent of the world, and (as he did ſometimes with <hi>Achitophel) turns them into fooliſhneſſe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Sam. 15 31, and 17, 14.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">2. In a way of Confuſion.</note> As God makes the wiſdome of the world fooliſhneſs in a <hi>way of Fruſtration,</hi> ſo alſo in a <hi>way of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion;</hi> in that he turns it <hi>againſt it ſelf:</hi> For ſo alſo he does, as we have it in the latter part of this 19<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
               <hi>verſe;</hi> proved by a Teſtimony out of <hi>Job, Ch.</hi> 5. <hi>v.</hi> 13. <hi>He ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the wiſe in their own craftineſſe,</hi> and <hi>the counſel of the froward is carryed headlong.</hi> This is that which God does with his Enemies and wicked men:<note place="margin">Pſal. 7.16. Exod. 18.11.</note> He brings <hi>their own miſchief upon their own head,</hi> and in <hi>the thing wherein they deal proudly, he is above them.</hi> Thus ye ſee the truth of the Point in the full proof and Explication of it, That the wiſdome of the world is fooliſhneſs with God. Firſt, Becauſe he <hi>counts</hi> it ſo. And ſecondly, Becauſe <hi>he makes</hi> it ſo.</p>
            <p>Would we now have ſome good account and reaſon given us of it, whence this comes to be ſo?<note place="margin">The Ground of the point.</note> It is very eaſie for us to have it; and that is this: Becauſe <hi>that</hi> deals ſo <hi>with him,</hi> as much as it <hi>can</hi> do. The <hi>wiſdome of God, that</hi> is fooliſhneſs with <hi>the world;</hi> and therefore the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the <hi>world, that</hi>'s fooliſhneſs alſo with God<note n="k" place="margin">Sapientia munda ſtultitia eſt apud D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um; hoc eſt, rationi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus caret apud Doum, quate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus eſt Author ſuper naturali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um: Nam ſtul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum eſt, quod fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne ratione eſt. <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>jetan.</hi>
               </note>: So he is but <hi>even and quit</hi> with them for it. As it is ſaid there, <hi>Zach.</hi> 11.8. <hi>My ſoul loathed them,</hi> and <hi>their ſoul ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horred me:</hi> Juſt ſo it is here. The <hi>world,</hi> that thinks ſcornfully of God, his Truth, and Waies, and Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and Children, and Miniſters; and he thinks as baſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of <hi>Them,</hi> their Counſels, and Projects, and Deſignes, and Practices, and the things which they take up to themſelves.</p>
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:166481:26"/>
            <p>What does all this now teach us by way of improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to our ſelves?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>The <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of all threefold.</hi> 1. To be of the mind of God.</note> Firſt, let us from hence learn to be of <hi>the mind of God himſelf:</hi> Let us think as <hi>he</hi> think in this particular. If worldly wiſdome be indeed fooliſhneſs with <hi>God,</hi> let it not then be wiſdome with <hi>us:</hi> Let not us then ſo much dote and rely upon it. There's a great Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument in it, from the <hi>Perſon</hi> who is here exhibited to us, which is much to be conſidered by us. The paſſing of any cenſure or verdict, is much according to <hi>him that paſſes it,</hi> what an one he is. And ſo it is here. It is a good obſervation of <hi>Auſtins</hi> upon that paſſage there in the Goſpel,<note place="margin">Luke 12.20.</note> 
               <hi>Thou fool,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Non ſic dicit Deus</hi> Stulte, <hi>quomodo Homo dicit: God does not call</hi> Fool, <hi>ſo as man calls fool:</hi> For man, <hi>he</hi> does it for the moſt part out of paſſion, and prejudice, and raſhneſs, and <hi>Folly</hi> it ſelf: But <hi>God,</hi> he does it alwayes <hi>diſcreetly,</hi> and for very good cauſe. We are ſure that the <hi>Judgement of God is accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to truth.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 2.2.</note> Therefore this may ſerve for the <hi>awakening</hi> of all ſuch perſons as thoſe are, which are no better af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected, which are no more but <hi>worldly wiſe,</hi> and do <hi>reſt and applaud</hi> themſelves in it, to think with themſelves this, that they are but <hi>fools</hi> in <hi>Gods account;</hi> which it may be, is more then at the preſent they do well conſider: If they <hi>did,</hi> it would make them more out of love with their Natural and Carnal condition.</p>
            <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">2 To deſpiſe this worlds cenſure.</note> We ſee here on the other ſide, how to <hi>ſet by the Cenſure of the world</hi> in that which at any time they lay and faſten upon us, eſpecially for <hi>doing of our Duties,</hi> and of that which belongs unto us: Not to weigh it, or to be moved with it. There are a great many Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans who are ſometimes much diſcouraged and hindred in themſelves from their Duty for fear of this, leſt the world ſhould cenſure them for it: Now, alas! what
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:166481:26"/>is the cenſure of the <hi>world,</hi> whoſe very <hi>wiſdom</hi> it ſelf is <hi>foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhneſs</hi> with the God of Wiſdom? Who cares much for the cenſure of a <hi>Fool?</hi> To be counted fooliſh by ſuch an one is no diſcredit or diſparagement at all. Now thus it is here; this is that which may ſatisfie us here in this buſineſs, that our Adverſaries themſelves are cenſured, and have folly laid to their charge, from whence they are diſabled in their ſentence:<note place="margin">1 Cor. 2.15.</note> 
               <hi>The Spiritual man judges all things, yet he himſelf is judged of no man,</hi> 1 Cor. 2.15. And whiles the world condemns the Church, it ſpeaks evil of thoſe things it does not know, nor is acquainted withall<note n="1" place="margin">Doctus novit indoctum, quia doctus ſuit. Sed indoctus nen no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit doctum, quia doctus non fuit. <hi>Adag. Arab.</hi>
               </note>. Well <hi>(Beloved)</hi> to draw up this Point; you ſee here now how it is? <hi>God</hi> and the <hi>world,</hi> they ſtand in a direct Oppoſition and Contrariety one to the other. The <hi>ſtrength</hi> of the world is <hi>weakneſs</hi> with God; the <hi>Friendſhip</hi> of the world is <hi>Enmitie</hi> with God; the <hi>VViſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> of the world is <hi>Fooliſhneſs</hi> with God; <hi>And that which is highly eſteemed among men,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 16.15.</note> 
               <hi>is an abomination in the ſight of God:</hi> And why then ſhould any of us be ſo glued and addicted to it, and to our opinions of it, as for the moſt part we are?</p>
            <p>Thirdly,<note place="margin">3. Not to glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in men.</note> Let us make the ſame Uſe of it which the Apoſtle himſelf makes in the Text and the Sequel of it, (which I hold to be ſtill moſt proper and natural in the handling of any Scripture) and what is that? ſee in <hi>ver.</hi> 21. of this Chapter, <hi>Therefore let no man glory in men, for all things are yours; whether Paul, or Apollo, or Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phas,</hi> &amp;c. Becauſe <hi>men</hi> are but <hi>men,</hi> even the <hi>beſt</hi> and <hi>wiſeſt</hi> that are, therefore not to <hi>glory</hi> in them, not to <hi>reſt</hi> upon them, not to <hi>attribute</hi> too much to them, not to <hi>wrangle</hi> and <hi>quarrel</hi> about them, but to think of them ſo as they are, and ſo to take them, and to make the beſt improvement of them that poſſibly wee can. And it
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:166481:27"/>holds eſpecially and more particularly as to the <hi>Miniſters</hi> in the variety of their Gifts and Abilities, not here to divide about them, and to take occaſion of <hi>making diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences</hi> from them, but with thankfulneſs to enjoy them <hi>all.</hi> I ſhall never have done if I ſay ſhall all which may be ſaid by me to this purpoſe; and therefore I muſt of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity break off whether I will or no. So now, I have done alſo with the <hi>Third General Part</hi> of the Text, which is the <hi>word of Inforcement,</hi> or Perſwaſion to that which was before adviſed, <hi>For the wiſdom of the world is Foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhneſs with God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>ANd now <hi>(Right Honourable and Beloved)</hi> whereas perhaps you may be ready to think that I have done with the Text,<note place="margin">The Appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the Text to the Occaſion.</note> yet I have not for all that, I muſt with your good leave go over it once againe before I diſmiſs it, or you with it (although not in ſo large a manner as I have hitherto done) and that ſo far forth as it carries a very good ſutableneſs and correſpondency in it to the preſent occaſion of your meeting together at this time, which me thinks it does very fully in all the ſeveral parts of it. This Scripture which I have now ſet before you, it is a good <hi>Item</hi> and Caution to you, to keep you from all thoſe Temptations which are ready to riſe up in the hearts of worldly men againſt the <hi>works of Charity,</hi> and Hoſpitality, and Liberalitie, and Beneficence to the poor. We will take notice of the Parts in their Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</p>
            <p>Firſt,<note place="margin">I. Of the Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> 
               <hi>Let no man deceive himſelf,</hi> It is a very good Preface and Introduction here, and ſuch as men have need of, as much as in any thing elſe; foraſmuch as in very truth there is nothing wherein for the moſt part they do more eaſily coozen themſelves then in matters of this
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:166481:27"/>
               <hi>Nature;</hi> whether faſtening on ſuch <hi>Arguments</hi> as may ſerve to keep them off from it, or nouriſhing ſuch <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples</hi> as do <hi>pervert</hi> and <hi>corrupt</hi> them in it. It is good for all ſuch perſons to be here awakened, and bid to take heed and to look to themſelves. We ſhall find that in <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.7. when the Apoſtle had premifed this Injun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, <hi>Let him that is taught in the word, communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate to him that teaches in all good things:</hi> He preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly adds hereupon, <hi>Be not deceived, God is not mocked.</hi> Why does he ſo? Becauſe men are commonly ſubject to put off ſuch Duties as theſe are from themſelves. And ſo may we now ſay here, when we are urging the works of Charity, and ſuch kind of Performances as theſe, <hi>Be not deceived,</hi> or <hi>Let no man deceive himſelf.</hi> Take heed of ſuch Colluſions and Falſe-reaſonings as thoſe are where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by men are hindred from ſuch a Work and Service as this is whereof we now ſpeak. That you may not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraud the poor, take heed firſt that ye delude not your ſelves, and your own hearts, which does lay ground, and make way for the other. Do not conſult with <hi>Fleſh and Blood,</hi> nor hearken to the ſuggeſtion of luſt and corru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption in ſuch a buſineſs as this; for if ye do, ye will quite undoe your ſelves, and others with you. It is good and ſafe for us, in every duty which God requires of us, to be ſtill moſt jealous and ſuſpicious of thoſe inclinations in us which are moſt favourable to our own eaſe and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal advantage, becauſe they are moſt likely to reſtrain us and interrupt us in it. And let that ſuffice for the Preface or Preamble or word of Caution, as applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to our preſent purpoſe, <hi>Let no man deceive him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now (ſecondly) I may apply to this likewiſe,<note place="margin">II. Of the Counſell.</note> even the <hi>Counſel and Exhortation it ſelf, If any man among you
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:166481:28"/>ſeemeth to be wiſe in this world, let him become a fool that he may be wiſe.</hi> Surely, if there be any men in the world that think themſelves <hi>Wiſe in the world,</hi>
               <note place="margin">—Populus me ſibilat, at mihi plaudo Ipſe domi, quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties nummos contemplor in arca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>Hor. de divite avaro.</hi>
               </note> it is thoſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly which are <hi>Rich in the world: The Rich man is wiſe in his own conceit,</hi> ſayes <hi>Solomon, Prov.</hi> 28.11. Whiles he lived he <hi>bleſt his ſoul, &amp;c.</hi> ſayes <hi>David (Pſal.</hi> 49.18) that is, he flattered and applauded himſelf. And we have an inſtance of it in the Goſpel, <hi>Luke</hi> 12.19. <hi>Soul, thou haſt much goods laid up for many yeers, take thine eaſe,</hi> &amp;c. Riches and Self Admiration (although I do not ſay <hi>alwayes,</hi> yet) <hi>very often</hi> go together. Unleſs it pleaſes God by his Grace wonderfully to reſtrain it, it is very rare for thoſe which are <hi>Wealthy,</hi> not to think too highly of themſelves, and to <hi>applaud themſelves</hi> in that condition: Therefore when the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> would in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct his Scholer <hi>Timothy</hi> what counſel to give to rich men,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 6.17.</note> he bids him, charge them that they be not <hi>high-minded, nor truſt in uncertain Riches;</hi> as laying the <hi>greateſt Caution</hi> there where was the <hi>greateſt danger.</hi> This is that which is here ſuppoſed and taken for granted, as that which, through man's corruption, lies in the very nature of the condition, without the more heed and caution. <hi>Rich men</hi> they are apt to think themſelves <hi>wiſe men,</hi> and to think themſelves the wiſer as they can hold their Riches the better, and keep themſelves from parting with them, though upon never ſo good an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion. There is a piece of worldly wiſdom which does keep off men of the world from thoſe good works which are to be done by them; and they are not commonly without their pretences, and carnal reaſons, and ſhifts, and excuſes, which they are pleaſed to make uſe of to this purpoſe.</p>
            <p>Well, but hear now whats the Apoſtles counſel and
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:166481:28"/>advice (us we may very well apply it) even to ſuch as theſe, <hi>If any man among you ſeemeth to be wiſe in this world, let him become a fool.</hi> A Fool: how is that? namely, by doing that which the world is ready to rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kon and judg of as Folly; <hi>viz. to do good, to be rich in good works, ready to diſtribute, willing to communicate,</hi> &amp;c. as you have it there propounded to you, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.18 Such perſons as are thus imployed, they are indeed the <hi>worlds fools,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 John 3.17.</note> yea, but they are Gods <hi>wiſe men;</hi> and ſuch as it becomes you to be, if you will be that which you ought, according as God does any way enable you for it; and you cannot diſcharge your ſelves of ſuch a Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty as this is without cloſing with it. I know that <hi>world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wiſdom</hi> will be ready (as I ſaid) to take up many Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments againſt it, and as much as may be, <hi>reaſon</hi> it out: but they are ſuch as the wiſdom of God is able very eaſily to ſcatter and bring to nothing.</p>
            <p>Oh (ſay ſome) but the Times are hard,<note place="margin">Objections anſwered.</note> Trading dead, Money ſcarce, the World uncertain; we would be willing to do ſome good with our Eſtates, but we know not what will become of us, nor how things may hereafter go with us. This at the firſt hearing may ſeem to have ſome what in it, but in good earneſt it will not hold water. It is not that which will excuſe you, nay, does rather in ſome reſpects more engage you: And ſo we ſhal find even the Holy Ghoſt himſelf to improve it, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 11.1,2. <hi>Caſt thy bread upon the waters, for thou ſhalt find it after many dayes: Give a portion to ſeven, and alſo to eight, for thou knoweſt not what evil ſhall be upon the earth.</hi> Becauſe the Times are hard and uncertaine, therefore thoſe whom God hath furniſhed with Eſtates above their Brethren, they ſhould be ſo much the more imparting of them, that ſo by this means they may do the greater
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:166481:29"/>good with them. For firſt, The <hi>greater</hi> is the <hi>Neceſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> the <hi>greater</hi> conſequently will be the <hi>Mercy:</hi> others diſtreſſes make our charity ſo much the more which we enlarge unto them: It is a Service more acceptable un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, more beneficial to men, more comfortable to our ſelves, and we ſhall hereby reap the greater fruit of the greater good which is done by us. But then, ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, (which is alſo expreſt in this Scripture) <hi>Becauſe thou knoweſt not what evil ſhall be upon the earth:</hi> Therefore do it upon this ground likewiſe, as being uncertain whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you ſhall have the like occaſions and opportunities afforded unto you. It is wiſdom for every man to do good whiles he may, to lay hold upon the preſent ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon which is adminiſtred unto him. And as for every thing elſe, ſo amongſt the reſt, for the works of Charity: <hi>Whiles you have opportunity</hi> (ſays the Apoſtle) <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.10. Give whiles you have it by you, the time may be when you have nothing to give, and then would give if you could, and wiſh that you had given already, when it will now be too late. This is the drift of the Preachers Argument, and ſo an anſwer to the fore mentioned Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection.</p>
            <p>Why, but (ſay ſome again) we know not whether our Gifts may hold; the times may be ſuch as the very <hi>matter</hi> and <hi>ſubject</hi> of our bounty may be taken away, Colledges, and Hoſpitals, and Almes-houſes, and places of Relief, they may not alwaies continue in being, and then what will become of all the Good which is done by us?</p>
            <p>This is ſtill a piece of the <hi>wiſdom</hi> condemned in the Text, but ſuch as hath no ſtrength in it. For firſt, Are ye ſure that your Eſtates will hold good hereafter in any <hi>other way</hi> beſides? thoſe Inheritances vvhich ye leave to
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:166481:29"/>your Poſterity, and thoſe Conveyances which you make to your Heirs, whoſoever they be: Can yee aſſure your ſelves of the continuance of them without any diſtracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? Will your <hi>own houſes</hi> continue for ever, <hi>and your dwelling places to all generations?</hi> and the Lands which ye call by your names, and the Wealth that ye leave to others which are related to you? Indeed, it may be (for <hi>ſome of you</hi>) <hi>your inward thought may be ſo,</hi> as it is ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied there in that place, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 49.10,11. but it is more then you can promiſe to your ſelves, or any one for you. And yet notwithſtanding is this no hinderance at all to you, for your care and endeavor about them, or your diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing them in ſuch a way as that is.</p>
            <p>But (ſecondly) Admit it to <hi>be ſo,</hi> yet is your <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement</hi> never the leſs, nor yet your <hi>Reward.</hi> We are to do that which is our <hi>Duty,</hi> and to leave the <hi>event</hi> of things to <hi>God</hi> to be ordered and diſpoſed by <hi>Him</hi> as himſelf pleaſes, who does not require of us to take care for the government of the world (being his own proper undertaking) but to do that which belongs to us in the places in which he hath ſet us. If we be but careful for our parts to do that good which is in our own power, we ſall have comfort and recompence for it, let things themſelves fal as they <hi>will,</hi> or as they <hi>may,</hi> for the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar iſſue and event of them. But I will not put Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons into your heads, and make them for you, ye can make them faſt enough you ſelves; but what ever they be of this nature, you muſt ſtill remember of what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition they are, and to what <hi>Head</hi> they do truly belong as the ſpring and riſe of them; namely, what is here ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt to us, the <hi>Wiſdom of the world,</hi> and accordingly make it your buſineſs <hi>thus far</hi> and in <hi>this ſenſe to be fools.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yea, and that for this Reaſon alſo which is here ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:166481:30"/>in the Text (to take in that too) <hi>that ſo ye may be wiſe men,</hi>
               <note place="margin">To be fools in a way of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, is wiſdom. 1. In the way of the world it ſelf.</note> which (no queſtion but) ye ſhall be in obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving; and that likewiſe in a two-fold explication. Firſt, in the very way of the <hi>world it ſelf,</hi> and within the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs of <hi>worldly wiſdome,</hi> go no further with it then <hi>ſo.</hi> He hat's thus a <hi>fool to the world,</hi> he ſhall by this means be <hi>wiſe</hi> to the world. We'l begin with it <hi>thus,</hi> My mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (in brief) is this, That by thoſe Acts of Charity and Bounty, and relief of the poor, whereby the world in the wiſdome of it, thinks an Eſtate is ſo much the more <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paraged,</hi> it is hereby ſo much the more <hi>advanced.</hi> And that eſpecially (which ye may take notice of) in three particulars.<note place="margin">Three wayes,</note> Firſt, In the increaſe of it. Secondly, In the comfort of it. Thirdly, In the ſecurity.</p>
            <p>Firſt,<note place="margin">1. As to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe.</note> for the <hi>increaſe:</hi> Obſerve <hi>it there.</hi> Its one Obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, which <hi>worldly wiſdome</hi> makes againſt works of Charity. Oh, I ſhall by this means diminiſh mine own Eſtate; the more I give to <hi>others,</hi> I ſhall have ſo much the leſs <hi>my ſelf.</hi> But, I pray, who told you ſo? Did you never read or hear in all your lives, <hi>of the Barrel of Meal that waſted not,</hi> and <hi>of the Cruſe of Oyl that failed not,</hi> to that <hi>Sareptane widow,</hi> that relieved the neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Prophet? You'll ſay, <hi>that</hi> was a <hi>Miracle:</hi> True, but ſuch an one as God works every day in the year in the proportion and equivalences of it. Believe it, and you will find it to be ſo. There's no man (I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident of it, mark what I ſay) which is one jot the worſe, no not in <hi>an outward</hi> and temporal reſpect, for any good that he does with his Eſtate, in ſuch a way as God does call him, and inable him to do it; but has it abundantly, one way or other, made up to him even in this preſent life: And there are many who have experience of it, that are able to bear witneſs to this truth, which I now de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver.
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:166481:30"/>If there be any, who ſometimes have ſuffered, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding their Bounty this way, it hath not been from <hi>that,</hi> if they ſearch and inquire into it, but rather from ſome other cauſe and occaſion, which has been joyn'd with it: nay, it may be, if it had not been for this, they had ſuffer'd more a great deal then they have <hi>done,</hi> and their loſſes had been ſo much heavier upon them then <hi>now</hi> they are. The Scripture is very full of promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of this nature, if we had but hearts to receive them, and ſo much faith, as to make tryal of them.</p>
            <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">2. To the comfort.</note> Add to this the <hi>comfort</hi> of it. Is there no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to be look'd after in an Eſtate, but onely the <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe</hi> of it? To have ſo much <hi>coming</hi> in? So many thouſands gathered together? Such Wares? Such Houſes? Such lands? Such heaps and treaſures of gold, and ſilver in great abundance? Alas! What is all this, if ye had as much as ye knew where to put it, if ye have not in the mean time <hi>a mind</hi> to take <hi>contentment</hi> in it? What's a <hi>Great Eſtate,</hi> with a ſad <hi>and diſconſolate ſpirit?</hi> I do not now ſpeak of it in a <hi>Religious</hi> way, but onely in a <hi>Natural.</hi> What is it to have large Revenues in a way of the world, and to have no delight or ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction <hi>in a mans ſelf,</hi> or thoſe about him? Beloved, ſhall I tell you? There's many a man in the world, which would make a very good and wiſe Bargain of it, even in <hi>a worldly conſideration,</hi> (to ſay no more) if he could pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe it ſo, to let go <hi>three</hi> parts of his Eſtate, that he might in joy but the comfort of the <hi>fourth;</hi> and I believe, that there are many of you, that hear me this day, who would with al your hearts cloſe with this offer, upon theſe conditions: See here now the moſt probable way, that may be, for the attaining unto it; namely, by doing good with thoſe Eſtates which God truſts you withall:
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:166481:31"/>this will ſanctifie and ſweeten, and put a gracious ſavour, and reliſh, and tincture upon all the reſt; make ye more comfortable in your <hi>ſelves,</hi> in your <hi>families,</hi> in your <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations,</hi> in your <hi>imployments,</hi> in all that ye either <hi>are,</hi> or <hi>have,</hi> or <hi>do: It is the Bleſsing of the Lord that maketh rich, and ADDS NO SORROW WITH IT. Pro.</hi> 10.22. And it is faithfulneſs in the uſe of Riches, which, as ſoon as any thing, does procure this <hi>BLESSING</hi> from him.</p>
            <p>Thirdly,<note place="margin">3. To the Security.</note> Take in to this further, the <hi>ſecurity</hi> of it; that's another thing which I know ye all deſire; to be <hi>ſure</hi> of that which ye have, that when ye have <hi>got</hi> it, ye may <hi>keep</hi> it, and that <hi>others</hi> may keep it <hi>after</hi> you, when you are gone, and in your Graves. This is as great a care as any thing, which thoſe that are Rich are exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſ'd withal: It is lookt upon as a great part of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries of <hi>theſe preſent times,</hi> that people can be ſure of nothing, whatſoever they injoy.</p>
            <p>It was never <hi>more uncertain Riches,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 6.17.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the <hi>diſ-appearance</hi> and vaniſhing of Wealth, then <hi>now</hi> it is. See here now, how to <hi>ſecure</hi> it as much as may be, and to make the beſt aſſurance of it that you can; namely, by laying out ſome of it to the relief of the poor <hi>Members of Chriſt.</hi> Put it into <hi>his</hi> hands, that is, into the hands of <hi>his Brethren;</hi> it is the ſureſt hold of any, and ſuch as will never fail.<note place="margin">Chryſologus.</note> 
               <hi>Manus pauperis est Gazophylacium Chriſti.</hi> The <hi>Hand of the poor, it is the Treaſury even of Chriſt himſelf,</hi> which needs neither Bolts nor Locks, nor Bars to faſten it with.</p>
            <p>This for <hi>your ſelves,</hi> whilſt ye are <hi>here.</hi> Now then af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards for <hi>your Children,</hi> when ye are gone <hi>hence</hi> (for I know ye take ſome care for <hi>them,</hi> and it is fit ye <hi>ſhould</hi>): Do ye deſire to ſecure your Eſtates in <hi>their</hi> hands? that
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:166481:31"/>firſt, neither they <hi>themſelves;</hi> may ſquander them away by ill-husbandry, (as many do after their Parents de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſe) nor yet that <hi>others may wrong</hi> them, and deprive them of them <hi>againſt their wills?</hi> Here's the way to this alſo, <hi>viz.</hi> By a Charitable imployment of that wealth which God hath given you; ye cannot better provide for your <hi>own</hi> Children, then by an helping, and relieving of <hi>others;</hi> theſe <hi>Widows, and Orphans, and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therleſs</hi> which are here before you, and ſuch as they; to whom you are Fathers, as well in a <hi>Politick</hi> ſenſe, as ye are to the other in a <hi>Natural;</hi> and when ye dye, ye ſhould make account, that there's a Childs Portion which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to <hi>them</hi> alſo: It is that, which by doing, ye might very much lay ground for the ſafety of all the reſt ye leave behind you.</p>
            <p>Thus ye ſee how by being as it were <hi>fools</hi> in the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and practice of the world, in this particular, ye ſhall become even <hi>wiſe</hi> to the world, and do that which will even promote you in <hi>worldly</hi> reſpects.</p>
            <p>But that's not <hi>all,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Wiſe for our Souls.</note> nor the <hi>chief</hi> which is to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered by you; ye ſhall by this means be alſo wiſe for your ſouls, and a better life; which is the beſt wiſdom of all. <hi>Provide Animae tuae bona in operibus bonis;</hi> as he ſaid. Ye provide good for your <hi>ſouls</hi> in good works, which are the better for them; not as they lye in <hi>opere operato,</hi> the works <hi>barely performed;</hi> but in the works together, with the <hi>Affections</hi> and Principles from whence they come. To do theſe things, and to do them out <hi>of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi> out of reſpect to <hi>God,</hi> who does <hi>command</hi> them; and love to your <hi>Brethren,</hi> who do partake of the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of them when they are done; <hi>thus</hi> they have a bleſſed and everlaſting Reward which does follow upon them. This is <hi>to lay up Treaſure in Heaven, where neither Moth
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:166481:32"/>nor Canker doth corrupt, nor Theeves break through and ſteal.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 16.9.</note> This is <hi>to make us friends of the Mammon of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſſe, that ſo when we fail, (that is, dye) they may receive us into everlaſting Habitations.</hi> This is <hi>to lay up in ſtore to our ſelves a good Foundation againſt the time to come,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 6.19.</note> 
               <hi>laying hold on Eternal life.</hi> So that if we think it is not enough for us, that in doing thus, we ſhall be <hi>wiſe to the world;</hi> yet at leaſt <hi>this</hi> may ſatisfie us, that by this means we ſhall <hi>be wiſe to God.</hi> And ſo ye have alſo the ſecond part of this Text in the Occaſional Application of it, <hi>viz:</hi> The Counſel or Exhortation.</p>
            <p>Ye may ſubjoyn,<note place="margin">III. Of the word of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forcement.</note> in the Third and laſt place, the word of Inforcement: <hi>For the wiſdome of this world is fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe with God.</hi> This is that which does quite daſh, and break in pieces all pretences and conceits of this nature whatſoever, which any people do frame to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, as impediments of them in theſe dutyes; that their wiſdome in this reſpect is but folly, and that with God himſelf. We read in the Goſpel, that when that <hi>good Husband</hi> (as he took himſelf to be) had pull'd down his Houſes, and inlarged his Barnes, and laid up his goods for many years, and that onely for <hi>himſelf</hi> (Soul, thou haſt goods laid up for <hi>THEE</hi>) and hereupon counted himſelf to be a <hi>very wiſe man;</hi> that <hi>the Lord</hi> thought O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe of him, and paſt another ſentence upon him; <hi>but</hi> GOD ſaid unto him, <hi>Thou fool, &amp;c.</hi> thereby ſhewing the oppoſition and contrariety of <hi>His</hi> judgement to <hi>his.</hi> And the ſame is that which he is ready to do alſo to any others of the ſame temper with him.</p>
            <p>To draw towards a Concluſion,<note place="margin">The ſumm of All.</note> Let all which hath been hitherto ſpoken to this purpoſe of theſe <hi>Duties and works of Charity,</hi> thus far prevail with your ſelves, as to perſwade you to the conſcionable obſerviation and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:166481:32"/>of them, as your own hearts do any thing tell you, that God has furniſht you, and inabled you for them. And let this (amongſt the reſt) be a ſpecial Argument to you for it; that it is the <hi>Buſineſs</hi> which ye are now met about <hi>for.</hi> Make not a Sermon a <hi>Complement,</hi> a matter of meer pomp, and courſe, and formality, but let it have its due efficacy with it, and let not the Ordinance of God go away without its errand, whereunto it is intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Oh, what an happy thing were it, if <hi>every Sermon</hi> which is Preached here upon this occaſion, might have the <hi>ſame ſucceſſe</hi> with it as <hi>that</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">A Sermon of Charity prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched to K. Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the <hi>Sixth</hi> by B<hi rend="sup">p</hi>. <hi>Ridley</hi> Martyr, the firſt occaſion of building theſe Hoſpitals.</note> 
               <hi>Sermon</hi> which firſt <hi>gave</hi> the occaſion!</p>
            <p>I hope it will ſo <hi>in part,</hi> yea, I doubt not of it. There are many occaſions and opportunities which are offered to you, and never more then in theſe ſad time wherein we live. If ever ye had occaſions given you for the exerciſe of <hi>true Charity, now</hi> ye have them. Many poor <hi>Families</hi> quite undone, which would be ſupported. Many <hi>young Beginners</hi> in Trade, which would be ſtock'd Many people which <hi>want imployment,</hi> that would be ſet on work. Many <hi>Aged,</hi> and paſt imployment, which would be relieved. Many <hi>ſick,</hi> and wounded, which would be healed. Sad, and diſconſolate, which would be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted. Diſtemper'd, and out of their wits, (poor crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures!) which would be reſtored. <hi>Reſtrained,</hi> and impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon'd for debt, which would be inlarged. <hi>Orphans,</hi> and friendleſs Children, which would be Educated and brought up. Give me leave to add <hi>one more,</hi> and not the leaſt conſiderable, <hi>Scholars</hi> at the <hi>Univerſities,</hi> which would be maintained, and incouraged in <hi>Learning.</hi> For by the way, let me tell you this, That Learning <hi>will</hi> be Learning, and <hi>must</hi> be, if <hi>England</hi> be <hi>England;</hi> it is but a <hi>Folly</hi> for any to think <hi>otherwiſe.</hi> The time may come,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:166481:33"/>when you will ſtand in <hi>need</hi> of Scholars, and would be glad to have them for your <hi>monie;</hi> and if ye be not careful to <hi>cheriſh</hi> them and maintaine them, where will ye have them? If ye ſet not young Plants, where will ye have grown Trees? Theſe are not like <hi>Jonahs gourd,</hi> to come up in a night (nor I hope will not be like his gourd neither, to go down in one) There is ſomewhat more belongs to it then ſo, and ſo you will find it. There are no extemporary <hi>Scholers,</hi> what ever there be of any thing elſe. As it is a matter of <hi>Induſtrie</hi> on their part, ſo it is a matter of <hi>Forecaſt</hi> on yours. It will therefore be a great piece of your Wiſdome <hi>here,</hi> by your care and bountie herein to provide for <hi>Poſteritie,</hi> and to prevent that Barbariſm, and Brutiſhneſs, and Savageneſs, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>civility in this particular, which in ſome mens thoughts, and apprehenſions, and expectations (I ſay not deſires) is coming upon us.</p>
            <p>Thus you ſee (Well Beloved in the Lord) how I have laboured with you all along, to draw you off to theſe <hi>Works of Charity,</hi> and Beneficence in every kind: but that is not all which I have to ſay to you; <hi>Qui monet ut facias, quod jam facis, &amp;c.</hi> I am further to add hereunto (both to Gods Glory and your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowne) what you have happily and worthily done <hi>al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready,</hi> for which the loynes of many Chriſtians daily bleſs you; The great Good which is continually done by your ſeveral Companies, and Societies, and Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porations, with ſo much <hi>Faithfulneſs,</hi> and <hi>Integrity,</hi> and <hi>Sincerity</hi> as indeed it is, would ſpeak for you there, where I my ſelf ſhould hold my peace. Yet I cannot but ſpeak it, and make mention of it both for incouragement and imitation.</p>
            <p>And that I may not altogether ſpeak <hi>without book,</hi> but
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:166481:33"/>may have ſome <hi>Ground</hi> for <hi>which</hi> I ſpeak, take a real ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of it out of this <hi>Paper</hi> which is put into my hands to preſent unto you.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Here followeth the great Coſt and Charges of the City towards the five Hoſpitals this year laſt paſt,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>AND now I have no more to ſay,<note place="margin">The Concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</note> but only <hi>Euge, &amp; Macte:</hi> Well done, and proceed ſtill in doing. You that have done well <hi>already,</hi> be perſwaded to <hi>go on</hi> and continue: You which have <hi>not,</hi> now at length to <hi>begin;</hi> it's never too late: You ſee here what a <hi>fair Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py</hi> you have ſet before; your next work will be to <hi>follow</hi> it, and to write after it. <hi>Vade TU, &amp; fac ſimiliter.</hi> It is that (which to ſay no more) God <hi>looks for</hi> from you, who wil not only call us to an account for <hi>good Precepts,</hi> but likewiſe for <hi>good Examples;</hi> not only for the <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels</hi> which have been given us, how far we have been wrought upon by them; but alſo for the <hi>Patterns</hi> we have had in our view, how far we have conform'd un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, as having from them <hi>greater advantage</hi> of being better, adminiſtred to us, if we had but impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved it.</p>
            <p>This (as I ſaid) is a main end of ſuch Aſſemblies and Performances as theſe in which we now are, which is not only to tel a <hi>fair ſtory</hi> of what hath been done here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore in former Ages <hi>(in diebus illis)</hi> through the Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Bountie of our Forefathers and Predeceſſors, but to ſignifie likewiſe what is to be done in Succeeding, by our ſelves after their examples, that ſo we may bee heirs, not only to their Eſtates, but to their Graces, and to the Comforts and Benefits which by Gods bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:166481:34"/>do attend thereupon in a Conformitie and Corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondency thereunto.</p>
            <p>Take one Argument more (for a cloſe) among ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other; The Ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>, and Dignitie, and Reputation of this <hi>Famous City</hi> (which you are intruſted withall, as well as with the <hi>ſafety</hi> of it:) This City which has been one of the great <hi>Wonders</hi> and <hi>Gloryes</hi> of the <hi>Chriſtian world</hi> for many Ages and Generations together, (and I hope it will be all our cares in our ſeveral places that it may be ſo ſtil) for the entertainment of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> for the incouragement of the <hi>Ministry,</hi> for the Grave and Comely and Well-ordered <hi>Government</hi> in it. And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the reſt, for this part of the <hi>State and Magnificence</hi> of it, in its Liberal and Bountiful Proviſion for the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of the Poor:</hi> That ſo as Pietie, and Juſtice, and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie may abound in it on one Hand, ſo alſo Peace, and Plentie and Proſperitie may anſwer it on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>This, for mine own part, I have very great Cauſe to <hi>wiſh</hi> and pray for, as out of the reſpects of <hi>common</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, ſo likewiſe of ſpecial and <hi>peculiar;</hi> not only as to the Place of mine own <hi>Birth</hi> and <hi>Education,</hi> but alſo of the Exerciſe of my <hi>Miniſtry and Theological Profesſion,</hi> which I do here now with a great deal of GRATE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FULNESS AND THANKFULNESS ACKNOWLEDG.</p>
            <p>It is time for me to have done, and ſo I ſhall; and the Concluſion which I will make, ſhall be that of the Prophet <hi>Davids</hi> concerning his <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſa. 1 22.3. &amp;c.</note> which I will apply in like manner to <hi>Ours. Let LONDON be a City compact, which is at Unity with it ſelf; whither the Tribes go up, the Tribes of the Lord to give thanks unto the
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:166481:34"/>Name of the Lord Pray ye for the Peace of LONDON; let them proſper that love thee! Peace be within thy walls and Proſperity within thy Palaces!</hi> For my Brethren and <hi>Companions ſakes, I will now ſay, Peace be within thee; yea, becauſe of the Houſe of the Lord our God, I will</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes <hi>wiſh thy Good.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>Pag. 13. lin. 4. <hi>for</hi> Spiritual r. ſpecial. p. 20. l. 7. r. rather <hi>then</hi> any. p. 52. l. 6. <hi>for</hi> too r. two. p. 56. l. 5. r. ſhall ſay.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
